righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations
and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song
the Lord of Spirits.
Firstienok, chapter 48, verses four through five.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge
but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the...
of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind
mankind through
throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, greetings, Dragon Slayer and Giant Killers.
You are listening to the 140th episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Interest Stephen Damick,
coming to you from the Three Martyrs studio
in Raleigh, North Kackalaki.
And with me as Father Stephen Damick,
waste deep, waste deep in the swamps of Lafayette, Louisiana.
And we are indeed live.
And that means that Mike Hassan DeGan
will be taking your calls starting.
in the second half. Now I have to, you know, we had that lead in again. Uh-huh. And I know
you probably don't have time to listen to a lot of stuff since you're now on staff at a Southern
mega church. Um, no lies detected as the kids say these days, but, uh, but, uh, and so you probably
I just heard that little bit right before we went live but
familiar with the talk. Do you know that person who who who let us in? You know
he had the unmitigated gall to say in that talk? No, what did he say? He said that
you should not publicly speak out and cause dissension against the spiritual
authorities God has put over you. What kind of nightmarish clericalism is this?
How dare he say? Yes, how did we take this in un-Christian, un-biblical, un-orthodox?
Yeah.
What unmitigated gole?
Let me just say yeah, okay go on go on. Yeah anyway
Well tonight we are gonna be discussing a group that anyone who's read the Bible has heard of and that's the Samaritan
So probably have some sense from the gospels the Jews and Samaritans don't get didn't get along
I don't actually I don't know much about the relationship these days
But where do these people come from what was their religion actually like and?
and what does does Samirium
anything within the Christian tradition large at large. So when we start with some historical
framing father in case people don't know about the whole north side south side thing.
They probably know there's at least one good one. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And if you're old enough,
You remember him smiling at you from the back of our v's.
when you're on road trips across America with Little Halo over his head.
Oh, yeah. Oh, man, that is an ancient deep cut right there.
There you go. So, uh, but yeah, we're not talking about that guy,
per se. Although, you know, if you're into the RV lifestyle,
you are welcome amongst our listeners. You've probably heard every episode.
Right? You've got some time. Uh,
But yeah, we're gonna talk about the Samaritans.
And we've got a bit of a,
cut night Joe thing going here.
Where did you come from? Where did you go, right?
And there are several places we could start, right?
And we are gonna loop around a little bit, right?
We could, we could start with the tribes,
we could start with the patriarchs
who the fathers are the tribes.
We're gonna loop back there,
but we're gonna start.
was sort of our historical survey in terms of where did the how did there come to be a Samaria
and Samaritans with a little bit of history of what happens when the kingdom divides the kingdom being
the kingdom of Israel. We have to remember that in terms of being a kingdom as we've said before
before we've got the timeline.
And the reason we reiterate this is that I think a lot of people have an exaggerated timeline in their heads.
Right.
So in terms of there being a king of Israel collectively, right, over all the tribes,
if we are generous and includes Saul.
Yeah. And as we said before on the show, Saul was...
less of a king and more of a war leader. He was basically there to lead the armies of the 12
tribes into battle. He did not have a capital city. Yeah. He did not have like a bureaucracy or anything
right and a court and all of these kinds of things that we associate with being a king and ruling
a kingdom but will be generous and include him. You're looking at a little over a hundred years.
Yeah, I'm an actual United Kingdom of all 12 tribes.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, because I mean, I think people have this idea that like, you know, thousands of years
or something like that, like that it was this, that the land of king and after was conquered
was this Israelite kingdom for at least centuries upon centuries.
And then some point then the Romans took it.
Right.
And so and
This is that number.
That number is also based on us being people who believe the Bible is true.
Right.
So you go and ask a secular old testament scholar, they're going to tell you David never existed
and Saul never existed.
Right.
And they're going to tell you, you know, they're never really, really truly was the United
Kingdom at all ever.
But we believe the Bible is true.
So not going to spend a lot of time already.
about the date of the Exodus because it borrows me, but regardless of whether you go for the early date, the late date, the even earlier date, right?
Where you peg the Exodus doesn't totally matter because basically that's an argument about how when the Exodus happened, when the conquest happened and then how long the period of the judges was.
Because we have a pretty good peg date for where
Saul and David and Solomon would be
And so we're talking about the very end of the 11th century BC would be where you get
Saul.
And by the end of the 10th century BC, the kingdom is of split.
Okay.
So that's if you want to know where that roughly 100 years is being generous again, you want
to know what 100 years that is, that's what 100 years that is.
That's when we're talking about in time.
And if you read the story of especially David closely, right?
Because Saul never tried.
It's not that Saul tried to establish a capital city in your bureaucracy.
It's up and failed.
He never tried.
Yeah.
Well, I mean, he was fulfilling what it is that the Israelites said that they wanted.
They wanted a king that would lead them out and, you know, bring them back in or whatever,
which is a war leader.
That's what they were looking for.
Right.
And so that's what he was doing.
And that's why every time we meet him, he's in a war camp.
right, whether it's going up against the Philistines, whether it's right, the Amulakites,
right, he's that's what he's doing. So he never tries. So it would have been, I mean, in a hypothetical
world where Saul didn't apostatize so horribly, right, it would have been presumably Jonathan
would have become king. And he would have done those things, right. But that's not the real world. So
So it's David.
who does those things.
And as you read the story of David,
and he frankly struggles to do those things,
you can already see during David's reign
that there are these tensions between North and South,
between the northern tribes that will become
the northern kingdom and Judah and Benjamin
and some of the Levites who are at the temple
who will become Judah.
Right? And this to the point that remember, David is made King of Judah before he's made King of all Israel.
The story of David, there are two separate coronations.
He's made King of Judah and then he has a rival, one of the sons of Saul, who's basically
being propped up as the next king in the North.
that gets resolved and then David is made king of everything.
But that so that tension is already there.
And if you know anything about US history,
you can see a parallel kind of thing.
Of course, we know about the northern states
and the southern states going to war in the American Civil War,
right in 1860s.
But before that, right, from 1776 on until the Civil War,
there are constant tensions between North and South, right?
right. Part of the reason Washington DC gets built as
a new capitalist because it's right on the border between the north and the south.
Right? That's why they picked that because this and other states were mad about Philadelphia
being the capital. Right? So, there are already these tensions. Right? There's already, they're
unified but not tightly. Right? And David is just beginning to set up. He starts the process.
I mean he captures the city of Jerusalem and makes it his capital.
Okay, didn't build a palace for himself.
Because he didn't want to do that until he had built a temple and God didn't let him
build a temple.
So there's only a temple and a palace in Jerusalem when Solomon builds them.
Right?
So David is really beginning the process.
Solomon really starts to do that.
part of the problem with Solomon's sin when you read about
in First Kings is the way he's going about doing that. So if you ask someone who's got in the
Sunday school version, right, you get, you know, Solomon had a thousand wives, right? Three
other wives, somebody occupies, right? And the problem is that he was sexually immoral.
Yeah. Is usually how it is kind of presented, right? Yeah. And but biblically, I mean, that's
right? And he's violating the the commandment in Deuteronomy that says the king is not to multiply
wives to himself, which a thousand. Yeah, you're. So that is a problem, but that's not the main problem.
The main problem. Solomon's main sin that gets the kingdom taken away from him or most of it
is the fact that
He was getting those wives. It wasn't just he was walking around the streets of Jerusalem and kept noticing pretty girls, right?
It was he was he was making these treaty deals. He was making these international agreements with his pagan neighboring nations.
to solidify rule within Israel, right? And in so doing the way those
So, this is the internet.
The national deals were sealed was by one of the daughters of that king becoming a wife of Solomon.
Yeah.
And then after that happened, right, that wife would come to live in Jerusalem with Solomon.
And oh, she would want to open a nice cultural center.
A Jerusalem aka a temple for a few of the
pagan gods that she worshiped back home. And I mean, you know, Solomon put even some
of them inside the temple to, yes, Yahweh the God of Israel. Yes, yes, we're told later
on because Josiah destroys it that Solomon had a chariot idol to the sun God that had
been worshipped in Jerusalem before David took it in the temple courts. Yep. Yeah, Shemist
... uh, it's a little... uh...
So yeah, so it was what's going on in the text is that this comparison is being
made between Solomon's sexual promiscuity and his spiritual promiscuity.
Right? That's what's at play sort of in the text. That Solomon's sin.
Right? And that's also the play that's going on with, that is the foolishness of the wisest man in the world.
Right. So there are several of these contradictions that play in the story of Solomon.
Right. And sort of paradox, he's a paradoxical kind of figure.
And so that situation is what results in.
authority over there know there are tribes being stripped away from him.
Right.
And let's go a little further.
What we're really seeing in the text.
Because first and second kings.
Are written.
Long after all of this happened.
Yes, or three or four kingdoms.
Yeah, 34th Kingdoms in your 6th Study Bible.
They're written in retrospect, right?
They weren't being written like as the things happened, right?
Like we did it too.
Yeah.
This is not a chronicle in the normal sense of a chronicle like.
And then this year, this is a stuff that happened.
And then this year, this is the stuff that happened.
Now that existed, right?
And you know how we know that?
Yes, we know that.
And then the text, it's right.
Yes, first and second gigs,
the fourth gig, it keeps referring to,
as to all the other stuff this gig did,
is it not in the annals of the gigs of Israel?
Right.
We don't have...
those unfortunately and the books and
articles are not are not those.
But the point being, you know, the king, the
king is doing fine on bragging about his
accomplishments. We will leave that to him.
Right. The biblical text is here to tell
us something else about these figures, right?
Not just to boast in their accomplishments. So
this is reading from the perspective. So
this is someone who whoever's writing this is
living in exile.
First is Hg Kings.
Very forth kingdom.
So he's very clearly be written by someone who's in exile before the return from exile.
Because there are a bunch of places, one of which we're going to read a little later tonight,
where the author keeps saying, until this very day.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
All right, he'll describe some of those they had
It's this way to this very day.
Well, that implies he's writing it at some distance
in the future from the event, right?
Otherwise saying until this very day
doesn't make a lot of sense, right?
If I say yesterday I made a bank deposit
and that money is in my account to this very day, right?
You'd be like, what?
Like, yeah.
So, right?
So there's some expense in time.
And so this is why it's called part
of the Deuteronomistic history.
Then when we're describing this part of the Old Testament is that the author is looking back at the history of Israel
Right leading up to its you know the destruction of the northern kingdom of the exile of the southern kingdom and he is interpreting it
He's explaining why things unfolded the way they did
And his basis sort of his interpretive lens is the book of Deuteronomy
So, for example, he sees in the book of Deuteronomy, kings are not to multiply wives to themselves.
Yeah.
You're not to know what some people say.
It's probably what some people say that God was totally cool with polychemy or something.
Yeah.
It's explicitly against the Torah.
And you're not to make these foreign agreements and you're not to build shrines to foreign gods and you're not to it right.
right and he sees all of these things and so as he looks back he says wow.
The kingdom of Israel as a whole fell apart very quickly
Right almost as soon as it was beginning it all fell apart
Why is that well he looked well Solomon?
Did all of these wicked things right according to the Torah according to the book of Deuteronomy
Right and so this was God's judgment
This was God's judgment.
And the reason I want to phrase it that way is that
part of what the Scriptures do, like when you're reading a historical book in the
Old Testament, it's not just communicating historical facts or even just
communicating a certain take on historical facts, but it's also modeling for us
how we should interpret and understand history, both events happening in the
world and events in our own lives.
Right? And there are lots of examples of this. The one I point to all the time in terms
of someone using this example is if you read the monastic sources and stuff about the
fall of Constantinople in 1453, they all say the same thing. They say, well, the bishops
and the last emperor and stuff had agreed to this union with Rome, this false union with
through.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. I mean, like the like the like the laments there are
for instance, there are laments written for the fall of concerts and Opal. And it's
basically about we have sinned. We need to repent. This happened to us because of our
sins. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. And more recently, after the fall of communism, the Russian people
people had long
periods of public collective repentance over what had happened to the Zars. They weren't
alive. Most of people have directly involved, were not alive. People who were still alive
were children, when the Bolshevik Revolution happened. Right? It was 75 years later. Right?
But that's how they interpreted history. So just a note here is we're going through this.
we're going to see this a lot. We're going to see that what we
get from the scriptures about this history, the history of Samaria that we're talking about tonight and whatever other history we want to talk about, is also a model for us of how to interpret and understand events, right?
Right, so judgment is coming down, right, for Solomon.
And so Solomon retains the title, King of Judah.
and successfully passes it on to his son, Rehobome,
which is that first coronation that David had,
but that second coronation never ends up happening.
And rather, God sends a prophet to somebody
we've talked about in a previous episode,
Jerobome son of Nebat,
who is not a good guy.
Yeah, I mean, he gets a sin named after him.
Yes. One thing you should get out of these texts is, you know, don't get a sin named after you.
Yes. Like the quest to commit a truly original sin should not be one that you're on.
Yes. So like the biblical, there aren't even that many biblical examples of this. No, there's the
sins of Jerobo, the son of Nebath and the sins of Balan. Yeah. I can think of off the top of my head.
bail in some of the or
You can make an argument for
Jezebel. That's a little, even that, that's a little strained.
So yeah, yeah, you've got to really, really mess up to get a sin named after you in the bubble.
But so Jeroboam, when you first meet him in the text, it doesn't look like it's going to be so bad,
right? It's, you know, hey, there's going to be this judgment on Solomon. But
the prophet of God says
to Jeroboam. He's going to remain the king of Judah and Benjamin because of what God
had sworn to David, his father. And so the Davidic line is going to remain in Judah, but he
makes the same offer to Jeroboam.
Yeah. Which is a judge. I was just saying, I think it's worth pointing out, by the way,
just because God makes this kind of offer to someone and even
says he's going to bless them. Does not mean they're a good guy.
Yes. Does not make them additional. Yeah. It's conditional.
He says at the time, right? He says, if you like my servant, David,
keep all of my commandments and walk in all of my ways, then I will bless you as
I blessed him and a child of your loins will sit on your throne forever.
Right?
So when that doesn't happen, it's not because God didn't keep us promise, because
Jeroboam, right, didn't fulfill the condition.
But it's worth noting.
I know we've touched on this at least briefly in the past, but it's worth noting, David
who kept all of God's commandments and walked it all his ways.
Except for the whole, you know, murdering a guy to cover up...
the fact that he got his wife pregnant.
Yeah.
Right.
And this is something we've pointed out,
but it's worth pointing out here too because of Jeroboam.
Right?
So this isn't saying, this isn't God setting a bar
that's impossible for Jeroboam to meet.
Yeah.
You know, oh yeah, I'll establish your dynasty, Jeroboam,
assuming you could be perfectly sinless.
the rest of your life, right?
No, it's just tested.
Do you like David?
Yes, do like David and repent when he sins.
You can sin very grievously, right?
As David did and repent, right?
And still meet this condition that God is giving, right?
So that's what he says to Jeroboam.
Jeroboam not only is wicked, but he does not repent and that's the problem.
So, Jeroboam is from the tribe of Ephraim.
This is important because the vast majority, like the largest tribe in all of Israel, was
Ephraim.
Largest number of people.
You can go through all the censuses in the Torah, right?
And that continued.
So it's the largest tribe which means because God apportioned the
land based on family units. Ephraim also controlled the most land of any of the tribes.
And Ephraim had gone in and taken most of their land. Yeah, because remember God told each
tribe take this part of the land, take this part of the land. This is your land. Right.
Because again, there was a condition.
That land was promised to them.
They had to go take it. If they didn't go take it, that wasn't God breaking his promise. That was them not meeting the condition. Right. And so we talked we talked before about how at the end of Joshua, even though a bunch of the tribes did not take their land, the end of the book of Joshua, it says God fulfilled all the promises he made to Abraham about the land.
Yep.
All right.
Sorry, dispensationalists, once again.
Um.
So Ephraim has the largest military of anybody.
If you throw in Manasseh, the other half tribe descended from Joseph.
So Ephraim and Manasseh, who were brothers, descended from Joseph.
Right.
If you throw the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh, you have almost all of the northern kingdom.
Yeah, because the rest of the tribes didn't actually go take their land that they were
supposed to take.
Right.
Like Dan did not take any of its land.
They went and attacked the city of Lai-
massacred everyone, renamed the city Dan, and they just had that city and its
environment, right, like the villages and stuff around the city. Right, so the
rest of those northern tribes remain small, right. Ruben was on the other side of
the Jordan in ever shrinking Moabite territory, but you can, you know, especially
if you're following the book of Judges, the wars with the Moabites and things, but
we won't go down that whole rabbit trail.
But so Ephraim in particular, and Ephraim and Manasseh, if you put them together, are almost
the entirety in terms of land, controlled by the Northern Kingdom and the vast majority
of the population.
So Jerobo and being in Ephraim I makes a lot of sense.
And this also is something that's kind of telegraphed in the book of Genesis.
This is something so weird.
We've heard all of these Bible stories
and they've gelled in different ways in our brains.
But if you can imagine a person who literally knows nothing
about the Bible, and they just pick up a Bible and say,
I'm going to start on page one and read through it.
And so they read the book of Genesis.
They read the whole book of Genesis.
they finish the book of Genesis.
Okay. The impression you get at the end of Book of Genesis, the story of Joseph is about
one-third of the Book of Genesis. Yeah. Right? Huge portion of the text is the story
of Joseph. And as you read the text, once you get to chapter 12 in the patriarchal narrative
start. It's Abraham.
right and then Isaac is considered his firstborn even though he's not technically the firstborn
right he's the firstborn from Sarah. Israel was technically the firstborn right son of Abraham right
and then you have Isaac has Jacob and Esau and Jacob is considered the firstborn even though he
He was kind of the second born because Esau was the first born.
Right, another twins.
He saw came out first, so he was technically first born.
Right?
But so you got Abraham, Isaac, Jacob.
And then if you've just read Genesis and nothing else,
Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Joseph.
Yeah.
Right?
That's who the focus shifts to.
And yes, Joseph isn't technically the first born Ruben is,
but Joseph is the first born from Rachel.
And all through the
story of Jacob, we're told over and over again that Rachel is the wife he loves. Right?
He gives Joseph the code of many color, right? The favorite, like, marking him out is the favorite,
right? And the first born. So you would walk away from the book of Genesis, expecting,
right? The rest of the Old Testament is going to be about Joseph and his descendants, and then maybe,
his brothers descendants also with him.
Right? Like.
That would be the normal expectation.
This is one of the things I point to, to argue that Genesis, as part of the Torah, has
to be way older than modern scholars want to admit.
Because if it was written after the destruction of the Northern Kingdom, why would you focus
so much on Joseph?
Yeah, it doesn't.
That's not the story of those people.
That's the story of those other people.
Right, because if you're writing later,
especially like after the exile,
like where Judah is the continuation,
wouldn't your focus be on Judah?
Oh, you get the story of Judah and Tamar,
that doesn't exactly make Judah look good.
Joseph comes out looking really good
at the end of Genesis.
Judah not so much, right?
Like, why would it look like that, unless it was written, you know, before all the other stuff happened?
Right?
But so there is this in the scriptures. There is this Ephraim I tradition. Ephraim is incredibly prominent.
Joseph is the most prominent among the sons of Jacob in the Torah. Ephraim is the biggest tribe, right?
Right, and that seed is a blessing from God, right?
They have the most territory. So they had the northern kingdom as Jeroboam is trying to now consolidate it as its own separate entity.
Right. As he's trying to do that, they have a heritage of the Torah they can point to. Right. They don't have to fabricate things. Right.
Right, they have, right, reason to say, hey, we're, we have a proud tradition too, right?
We have, have this thing.
So we immediately problem is we run an immediate problems with how
Jeroboam goes about it. Right so Jeroboam for example decides it's a big
problem that the temple is in Judas territory. Yeah so I set up a zone deal. Yeah.
And so people have to go there to worship and so he sets up a golden calf at Dan
all the way in the north end of the kingdom and Bethel all the way down in the
south into the kingdom.
It says, hey, you can just go off your sacrifices to Yahweh there.
Yeah, it's basically a dollar-trish worship of Yahweh.
Right.
And that becomes sort of the state cult.
Right?
And make no mistake, as before this, you read the text closely, he was paying Levites
to do this.
Right?
There were apostate Levites.
Not all the Levites were at the temple.
That's why I...
I always say when I'm talking about Judah, I always say some of the Levites.
Right?
There are Levites who are working for higher.
If you read the end of the book of Judges, there's a Levite who's getting paid to offer
sacrifices to a silver idol in Dan.
Right?
So, you could, they could in the Northern Kingdom accept the Levites being the priests without
necessarily
accepting the temple or actually following the other commandments regarding worship, right?
So he has his own Levites on the payroll of the new Monarchy who are doing the sacrifices at Bethel and Dan
That becomes the state religion, right? That is
The sin of Jericho and the son of Nebat, right?
And what is the core of that sin?
The core of that sin?
is he is very deliberately taking the people who he's supposed to lead. And rather than
using the Torah as his guide for how to lead these Israelite people, he is instead leading
them in the opposite direction. He is leading them into idolatry and expressly away from
the correct worship of God.
And so...
We end up early on we get a couple of dynasties very fast
Jeroboam's son gets killed and
Replaced by his killer
Who reigns for a little while and then turns it over to his son who gets killed
And
See there's a there's an important connection here
that the text is making between political corruption and spiritual corruption.
Those are two things that go together.
Again, there's not this separation that we have in our heads.
Like material things that are spiritual things.
Well, that guy has a Christian, he's just totally corrupt.
Right.
can't really separate faith in morals that way.
But also, if your culture and your society
is involved in false worship,
in the worship of false gods,
or worshiping a complete misunderstanding of God,
or worshiping God in idolatry,
so therefore serve utilitarian manner, et cetera, et cetera.
Then it is going to be corrupted if it's not corrupt already.
Right, you can't separate those two.
So that happens and if you want ultimate level corruption every few years, you've got
a new king because someone killed the old one and took his place, right?
That's not political stability.
That's not helping any one prosper in your nation.
That is bad in all ways.
So then, omery comes to power.
Oh
established as the Omride dynasty, which is going to be the longest lasting though
that's not saying much. Northern kingdom, but most infamous dynasty of the
Northern kingdom. So Omrie is the one who raises the Northern Kingdom, which is
called Israel to be an
actual geopolitical player.
To being important, right?
So we all know about this talks of smack on Lichtenstein.
There's some countries that are perfectly good countries,
but they're not big players.
It's true.
In geopolitics, right?
I mean, Switzerland has banks at least,
but you know, Lichtenstein,
No, no one is gonna be in
invaded by the federated states of Micronesia.
Yes, yes.
Tonga is not attacking anybody, right?
Yeah.
OK.
So there are big players.
There are not big players.
So you're the king of Israel becomes a player, right?
Gets dealt into the game of geopolitics under Omri.
And this is true to the point that when
we find some of our
earliest inscriptions that talk about the nation of Israel, right, as a nation.
They refer to it as bait omri, the house of omri.
Yeah, so it means he's considered to be such an important person that it gets named after
him.
They're not even calling it bait Ephraim or something like that.
No, it's not bait Ephraim, not bait.
It's right.
uh, uh, bait omray. Um.
And this is true to the point that here's a certain amount of irony, not like rain on your wedding day. No actual irony.
That we have an inscription, you could go see it if you're at the British Museum.
That depicts J. Who?
A much later king of the Northern Kingdom.
This is where the irony comes in.
Who is the one who finally wipes-
out the Omride dynasty depicts him and refers to him as J.H. of the House of Omri.
Wow.
Because they were everybody else was still calling the country that, the nation that even though
this guy had wiped out Omri's dynasty.
So there's that, right?
So that shows you the shadow of Omery.
I mean, he is everybody remembers Jeroboam.
There's a Jeroboam the second very near the end, right?
So I mean, he's there as a founder.
The shrines are there and stuff in terms of the official religion.
But if you want the George Washington of the Northern Kingdom, it's Omray.
If you want the guy, right, who makes makes them great
as far as they ever were, it's omery.
Now, despite all that, he gets eight verses devoted to him in the Bible.
Let's say, yeah, like, like if you're only knowledge of ancient Israelite history is the Bible,
you would not think that Omri was that big of a deal.
Yes.
Yeah, we have multiples more written about him
outside the Bible that inside the Bible.
Yes, so the world basically thought that he was a really big deal, whereas the biblical writers are like, eh,
not so much. And in fact, here is what they say about him. Yeah, okay. So this is first king 16,
also known as third kingdoms, starting with verse 21. Then the people of Israel were divided into two parts.
Half of the people followed Tiffany, the son of Gennath, to make him king, and half followed Omri.
But the people who followed on re-
overcame the people who followed Tiffany the son of Genneth. So Tiffany died and Omri became
king. Let me let me five for a second. Yeah, yeah, good. That a great euphemism. That followed
what happened the other. But Omri's people overcame them and Tiffany died. Yeah, he just died.
I'm just tired.
Okay.
How did he die?
I don't know.
Yeah.
Okay.
So verse 23.
In the 30.
first year of Asa, King of Judah, Omri began to reign over Israel and he
reigned for 12 years, six years he reigned in Tirza. He bought the hill of
Samaria from Shemur for two talents of silver. That's a lot of money, by the way
everybody. And he fortified the hill and called the name of the city that he
built Samaria after the name of Shemur, the owner of the hill. Omri did what
was evil in the side of the Lord and did more evil than all who were before
for him.
walked in all the way of Jeroboam, the son of Nabat, and in the sins that he made Israel to sin,
provoking the Lord, the God of Israel, to anger by their idols. Now the rest of the acts of
Omri that he did in the might that he showed, are they not written in the book of the Chronicles of
the Kings of Israel? And Omri slept with his fathers and was buried in Samaria and Ahab, his son
reigned in his place. That's a name that probably people recognize. Yes, yes. He's the most famous
Umoride that you know about. Yeah.
So eight verses.
That's it.
And what is the context?
Well, he killed his opposition and took the throne.
He bought a hill.
And he was evil that he died.
That's the Bible's take on the Great Omnory.
If you want to know more, you can hear a bragging about himself
in his own annals.
Right.
Yeah.
That's it.
So the important part here, right, in terms of the history, is, hey, Samaria, right?
Yeah.
Which in adhibru is Shamron.
So Shamir is the guy he buys it from.
He names it Shamron after the guy he bought it from.
Yeah.
It's an inspiring story of how you name the place.
That's a little bit...
of comedy there in the text, believe it or not.
That's like, there's no real significance to the name, right?
Basically what they're saying.
Samaria, right?
Because basically because Greeks don't make the sound, it's not a sounding Greek.
Samaria, you can hear out, Shamir, Shamran, Samaria.
They don't like ending names with a new Samaria.
Right, right.
I think I'm so very...
Yeah, so and so he buys that hill and he builds the capital city on it, right?
That becomes the capital. So that's why it says he rained for six years in Terza.
Then he buys the hill. That's a new capital and Samaria the city of Samaria on that hill that fortified hill and you build
cities in the ancient Near East on hills because you can then build walls
around the rim of the hill. That makes the very hard to lay
to you too because you have to
go uphill to get to the wall even, right? Everybody can see you coming, et cetera, right?
So, similarly, we have a good question in the chat, which is relevant to this point right
here in the story. So, Katie asks, where all the tribes basically like independent of
each other was due to unaware of Ephraim and their golden calf, or would they be aware?
So what is the political situation between the tribes at this point?
So between the two kingdoms, I think is where that's going, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yes, they're aware of each other and they're varying levels of hostile toward each other.
Right.
This point that hasn't erupted into anything because Judah is very small and until Omri is the Northern
the visual is very unstable.
Right.
So, later on, this is going to erupt into, like the Cereo-Ephryomite War is not between
the Syrians and the Ephraimites.
It's the Syrians and the Ephraimites, the Ephraimites being the Northern Kingdom, right,
being Israel, attacking Judah.
Yeah.
And I mean, remember the other tribes in the North basically didn't take the land they
were supposed to take, so they all remained relatively small, and that's why Ephraim
dominates the Northern.
kingdom. Right. Right. So Dan is so small, they're not going to be self-supporting with
basically one city and its environs. Yeah. So they basically team up with they team up
with the big guy. Right. And so they border it anyway. Right. So just become part of it.
Now you've got access to the infrastructure trade on and on and on. Right. Protection
from invasion, right? One city alone trying to defend itself. Good luck.
right? So yeah, for all those reasons, the smaller tribes are staying attached
to Ephraim. The smaller, less powerful tribes in the north. So yeah, so
some areas remains the capital city all the way until the fall of the northern
kingdom of Israel to the Assyrians. Okay. People are probably pretty aware of
Hey.
We have Omri's son and his wife, Jezebel.
We've talked about her and him, although he's basically an appendage of her.
That's what she bosses around.
In the past, I'll show it in various contexts.
As you can tell from her name, which contains the name Bale.
As a tip, but Jezebel was probably not.
her actual name.
Huh?
Because Jezebel in Hebrew means where is bail?
Yes, kind of.
They probably best with her name.
They can.
Yeah, that's a light just joke.
Remember, like, hey, where babies in the bathroom?
Maybe he's on vacation, right?
Um, so yeah, they probably, so her name was probably something more,
like something giving praise to bail.
and
writer of scripture did not want to say anything in praise of Bale and so flipped it.
And the same way that Saul, like King Saul, had a son named Ishmael, man of Bale. But in the Hebrew
text it refers to him as Ishma Shet, which means man of shame instead of man of Bale.
So that's a very common thing in the biblical
right? They're not going to write something saying bail or the title,
Baal Zabool, meaning great Lord Baal gets turned into Baal Zabub, the Lord of the Flies.
Lord of the Flies, yeah. Yeah. So yeah. And probably that happens with Jezebel.
But the whole story with that with the prophet Elijah, the prophet Elijah, Jezebel.
So, Jezebel is the daughter of the King of Sidon, and so much like...
What Solomon did, Omri made a deal, part of him entering the geopolitical scene made a deal with the King of Sidon, meaning he made a deal with the Phoenicians, trade deals.
And how do you seal that deal?
You married his son, Ahab, to the daughter of the King of
Siden, namely Jezebel, and Jezebel, just like with Solomon,
brought with her bail worship.
Yeah, big time.
So now you've got two layers of bad religion in...
apologies to Greg Gavin in the North or the Kingdom of Israel.
You've got the state religion of the golden calves and you've got bail worship at high
places.
Right?
So it's sort of doubly bad.
And she begins to murder the prophets of Yahweh.
That's where we're first introduced to her.
That ends up, of course, getting turned around on the profits of bail after...
caramel and A have in Jezebel have judgment pronounced against them. Jezebel heads up
falling off a wall and getting eaten by dogs.
Dogs. One of them have good streets. Yeah, it's been good. Yeah, I mean,
third, fourth kingdoms, first, second kings. You got a lot of these characters get
Game of Thrones endings man.
Uh, yeah.
Uh, you have done...
guys in battle. We've talked about that whole episode before, but not only that, there's
now going to be judgment against the whole dynasty, right? And part of what ends up
bringing about judgment against the whole dynasty and ensuring that is a not so nice lady
named Atholaya. And who is that? Yeah. And Atholaya, interesting, the YAH at the end of
athelaya
Is abbreviation of Yahweh. Yeah, that's all Yah. Yeah, and why would that be? Well, this is the Yahweh
of the state religion in the north, the Golden Caves. Oh, there Yahweh. Yes. And she was buried off
in a trade deal. She's descended from Ahab. She's an Omride Princess in the northern kingdom.
She gets married off to...
the son of the king of Judah. So marrying south as it were. Yes. And so, uh,
and then things get worse because you may remember from way back the long ago
time, long time listeners, you may remember that in the southern kingdom of Judah
unlike the northern kingdom and most other kingdoms of the ancient Near East,
There was an office of the Gibirah. There was an office of...
Queen Mother. This began with Solomon. Solomon had a throne that it is right hand for his mother, Bathsheba.
And she was considered the closest advisor to the king and therefore had a position of power within
the kingdom. And this is why as you go through, first and second kings are 34 kingdoms. Every time
you have a new king of Judah take the
a new divinant king takes the throne, it tells you the name of their mother.
There are some people who will try to say, well, that's just because of polygamy.
Well, that's partially true.
In the sense that, you know, the wife of the previous king who became the queen mother
was the one who was the mother of the new king, not just one of his wives in general, right?
not his first wife necessarily or senior wife or whatever preferred wife, but the actual mother of the king.
But you don't see that in the Northern Kingdom and they were just as polygamists in the Northern Kingdom, if not more so.
You don't see that in the neighboring kingdoms around Israel and Judah.
That's a peculiarity of Judah.
Judah's monarchy is this office of Queen Mother.
And as we pointed out the past, when we talk about this,
This is why it is
very Jewish. It is built into the idea of the Messiah, the Messiah Ben Dawid. Right? The Messiah
son of David, right? That when you have the Messiah, the son of David, when he is enthroned,
you expect the announcement of the name of his mother.
And you expect his mother to be at his right hand.
right as the closest advisor in his kingdom.
It's eminently biblical.
Okay. As we have covered it linked in the past.
Yes. So it's already up to his friends on that one.
But that doesn't mean that every person who held this office was a good person.
Right. Right. Just like most of the kings were not good kings in the Old Testament.
I'm sorry.
Atholaya gets this.
office and is a very bad person because her husband dies. Her son now is king but is a child.
So guess who's running things? Yeah.
Atholaya. And she decides to use that power to try to wipe out all the rest of the line of David.
Yeah, basically merging Judah and Benjamin into the epimydement of the effect of yes,
yes, try to effectively annex them and destroy the Davidic monarchy.
Yeah, which of course does not work.
Right. Does not end up working.
And in fact, is sort of the last straw rough justice happens.
and it's actually the Omride Dynasty.
It's actually...
the descendants of Ahab who get completely wiped out. And that slaughter gets finished under J.
Who we mentioned earlier, who then becomes the king of the Northern Kingdom of Israel.
Very near to the end of its existence. So looking at Israel's history,
as we've just gone over it, very brief, right? We're not going to read through all of
Yeah.
first and second kings, sorry guys who wanted that.
I will do that eventually on whole council of God and it is in the archives.
But there's this tension within the history.
So without a doubt, there's not a tension in the sense that like
you know there's good things and there's bad things.
Right, like it's pretty wicked all the way through.
Right?
We don't get a Josiah.
And then over there.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, they get some pretty, pretty big deal profits though.
Big deal profits.
They're certainly the kings.
In terms of the kings.
Right.
There's not even a brief period where they're not idolatrous.
Like, religiously, they're idolatrous from the start.
And it really gets worse once you get bail and other gods coming in.
So there's never a period where that's on the right track.
aren't good.
Just righteous kings right but but even though they're that way for the start God doesn't just write them off
He keeps sending the prophets and not just any prophets
Yeah, okay Elijah
Elijah Jonah is originally a prophet to the northern kingdom and others and actually Jonah
Traditionally considered a successor to Elisha a lot of people don't yes
Yes
So, right, so these are...
major prophets, right? It's not, you know, God's really focused on Judah, but, you know, some of the
crumbs fall from the table and go to the northern kingdom. He is just as if not more involved in trying to
call the northern kingdom to repentance as he is with the southern kingdom through his prophets.
Yeah. So the northern king was very much not written off. That's why I say there's this tension,
Right? There's this tension that God still...
loves them, right? They are still part of Israel. They are still part of his people,
a very wicked part, but still part, right? And that's the tension, right?
And then sort of the end for them comes. And we're still not reading the whole
versus the second Kings, but we are going to read a chunk here.
Yeah, and we're gonna pause and go through parts of it
because the details of the fall of the Northern Kingdom,
the fall of the Kingdom of Israel,
get passed over very quickly sometimes.
Right?
I mean, we have on this show in the past,
just refer to the Syrians come, they deport everybody.
Right?
Like, you know, just, it sure.
And then the Assyrians came.
Yeah.
Right.
And they were very bad.
Um, yeah.
The, the, the, the, the,
I like to say that the worst people in the world at the time.
Yeah, but when you actually read it in second Kings or fourth kingdoms, this is one of the passages in
First and second Kings or third or fourth kingdoms
That most clearly and obviously and unambiguously is doing what I talked about earlier
Hmm, right. It's almost like the author turns to the camera and
And it's like, okay, here's why this is happening.
See all this horror happening behind me? This is why, right? Like it's like editorial, right?
Yeah. Okay. Second Kings, also known as the Fourth Kingdoms, chapters 17, starting with verse 6.
In the ninth year of Hosea, the king of Assyria captured Samaria, and he carried the Israelites
a way to Assyria and place them in Hala and on the Hala
the river of Gozhan and in the cities of the Meeds.
And this occurred because the people of Israel
had sinned against the Lord their God who had brought them up out of the land of Egypt
from under the hand of Pharaoh, King of Egypt, and had feared other gods
and walked in the customs of the nations,
whom the Lord drove out before the people of Israel.
And in the customs of the kings of Israel had practiced.
And the people of Israel did secretly against the Lord their God
things that were not right.
They built for themselves high places in other towns from
watched our fortified city, they set up for themselves pillars and asherim on every high hill and under every green tree, and there they made offerings on all the high places as the nations did whom the Lord carried away before them, and they did wicked things, provoking the Lord to anger, and they served idols of which the Lord had said to them, you shall not do this.
Yet the Lord warned Israel and Judah by every prophet and every seer saying,
Turn from your evil ways and keep my commandments and my statutes in a court.
with all the law that I commanded your fathers, and that I sent to you by my servants the prophets,
but they would not listen, but were stubborn as their fathers had been, who did not believe in the
Lord their God. By the way, that doesn't pause. That they were atheists. Yeah, let's pause
there a second. Let's pause there. Yeah. Yeah. This is one of the most obvious
where the word believe actually means faithful. They were not faithful to the Lord their God. Yeah.
So.
Listen to the narrative, we get a recap. Right? We get a narrative recap here. So we're informed, okay, the series come, they capture Subarion, they take the capital. Right? That means, you know, it's over. Right. Pack it in.
But then it turns editorial and we get the story and it goes all the way back. Right? Because these are people. These tribes.
There are ancestors who God brought out of the land of Egypt and brought out of slavery.
It starts with what God had done for them.
And he brought them there to that land and noticed the reference.
He drove out the wicked people who were there before them and gave that land to them.
And then what did they do in return?
Did all this good and what did they do in return?
They did all the things that those people who had been driven out did.
you
Every hill, there's a pillar.
Every tree turned into an ashram.
Right?
Obviously that's not literally every tree.
Right.
Okay.
And not literally every...
But you get the point, right?
It's a little bit of hyperbole.
I know people have trouble with hyperbole sometimes, but...
Right?
So...
But they did this and they provoked God to anger.
Right?
God would have been
right at that point because he told them in the Torah, he told them when he brought them
and he said, if you become like the people I'd row out, I will drive you out as well.
Right?
They have been warned.
At that point God could have destroyed them.
But here the text wants us to know that that's not how God responded.
It's netty sent them prophets.
Yeah.
Right again, there's a little hyperbole every profit in every seer right
like if he's going to want right they came and said hey you need to repent you need to stop what
you're doing repent keep my commandments right and you will be blessed right that's what he wants
God does not delight in the death of a sinner but that they turn and live right
says to the prophets but what but they wouldn't listen to the prophets they were stubborn
They wouldn't be faithful.
Right?
This is, right, this is in capsule form.
This is what Christ keeps saying to the Jewish leaders in the Gospels.
Here's everything God has done for you.
You are wicked in response.
It's all he sent you prophets.
You
he's set you his son. Right? Why? To call you to repentance? Why? Because he loves you.
He doesn't want to see disaster but fall you despite your wickedness,
despite your ingratitude, despite your in hatred of him, but your stubborn and you won't listen.
Right? And that's when disaster comes. Right? That's what when when Christ appeals to the prophets
and talks about them killing the profits of the...
This is what he's referring to. The historical example that they have in their own scriptures,
that they're repeating as they persecute Christ and seek His death.
Ready to roll on here? Yes. Okay, picking up with verse 13,
they despised the statutes and his covenant that he made with their fathers and the warnings that he
gave them. They went after false idols and
became false, and they followed the nations that were around them, concerning whom the
Lord had commanded them that they should not do like them.
And they abandoned all the commandments of the Lord their God and made for themselves
metal images of two calves, and they made an ashera and worshiped all the host of heaven
and served bail.
And they burned their sons and their daughters' offerings and used divination and omens,
and sold themselves to do evil on the side of the Lord, provoking him to anger.
Therefore, the Lord was very angry with Israel and
removed them out of his sight. None was left but the tribe of Judah only. Judah also did. Yeah. Yeah.
The thick of pause there. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So notice it says, you're
I've removed them out of his sight, right?
And none was left with drive of Judah only.
So the reason I wanna...
pause on this is, right? There have been people historically, and even to this day, who
take that literally. Yeah. We want to say, no, that's literal. There are no, there were
no descendants left in the land of any of the northern tribes. Yeah, completely emptied
out, supposedly. Yes. Now, there's a pile of problems with this from modern genetic testing
people from the
than tribes who show up later in the biblical narrative, you know, handful of individuals,
but still, right? And also just the fact we've already seen in this particular piece of
text, a bunch of hyperbole. They did not literally turn every tree into an ashera pole, right?
We did not literally have it pay get ultra on every single hill.
Right.
This is hyperbole.
And so the idea is that just as their rebellion was sort of complete or total, right, the
judgment against them is complete and total, right.
But it's not trying to be taken in a sense that there are like no, not a single zero numerically
zero survivors left in the lamp.
Okay.
Go ahead.
All right picking up with verse 19
Judah also did not keep the commandments of the Lord their God but walked in the
customs that Israel had introduced and the Lord rejected all the descendants of
Israel and afflicted them and gave them into the hand of plunderers until he had
cast them out of his sight. When he had torn Israel from the house of David, they
made Jeroboam the son of Nabat King and Jeroboam drove Israel from following the
Lord and made them commit great sin. You can hear that this is basically like,
This is an overview of everything that has just happened.
Yes, the worst hits.
Yes.
Exactly.
The people of Israel walked in all the sins that Jeroboam did.
They did not depart from them until the Lord removed Israel out of his sight as he had
spoken by all his servants, the prophets.
So Israel was exiled from their own land to Assyria until this day.
And the king of Assyria brought people from Babylon, Kuthah, Ava, Hamath, and Sephar
and place them in the cities of Samaria instead of the people
people of Israel, and they took possession of Samaria and lived in its cities.
And at the beginning of their dwelling there, they did not fear the Lord.
Therefore, the Lord sent lions among them, which killed some of them.
So the king of a Syria was still...
Let's pause.
Let's pause for a second.
Yeah, interesting.
That's kind of odd, right?
Like probably people had read that before, right?
This is kind of a...
Wait a minute.
What?
Right.
But you're taking show up.
Yeah, pagans show up, they settle in the cities and then lions sort of attacking them.
And which just text says that God sent the lions.
Yes, God sends lions just to make it like, yeah, like this is some kind of weird horror
movie, like a jaws spin off, right?
But with lions.
The, so the idea here is who's land is it anyway?
Right?
Yeah.
Gods, right?
And that was the whole point back of the Torah.
That land and, frankly, all the land that there is, the whole world, right?
The whole cosmos belongs to God.
And so, especially that part.
Yeah, God could decide who's going to live there.
And that's what he said to them.
That meant God could remove the giant clans in front of Israel.
That meant if Israel became wicked like them, God would remove them, right?
replace them with someone.
else. Okay? So this replacement happens under the Assyrians. Okay? But the people who
the Assyrians send in to resettle the area after deporting the Israelites right from
the get-go are pagans and not worshipping Yahweh the God of Israel. Yeah, they're worshipping
their own cuts, which is the problem. That's why God removes people from that land.
this for
worshiping other gods, right? And so because there isn't a human judge there, right, or an Israel
there anymore, through which God can enact his judgment against those newcomers, the land itself
sends lions. The land itself sends wild animals, and the land itself does not cooperate with them
them in their crops, right?
The land is...
itself rebels against their wickedness. Right? And so this is a problem. Right? And now
we're going to hear about how this problem gets solved. This is important for where we're
going tonight. Okay, verse 26. So the king of Assyria was told, the nations that you have
carried away and placed in the cities of Samaria, do not know the law of the God of the land.
Therefore he is sent to lions among them and behold there
killing them because they do not know the law of the God of the land. Then the King of Assyria
commanded, send there one of the priests whom you carried away from there and let him go and
dwell there and teach them the law of the God of the land. So one of the priests whom they had carried
away from Samaria came and lived in Bethel and taught them how they should fear the Lord.
right every nation yeah so what are the Levites gets sent back yeah right and
is who? It's pagans. These Gentile pagans, right? And whoever was left, right? Whatever
other survivors were around, right? But teaches them what? teaches them the Torah. Yeah.
Teachers of the Torah and to worship Yahweh the God of Israel. It's kind of an early evangelistic
moment really. Yes, it's almost slur
We've got a big group of Gentiles coming into a place, the northern tribes.
There you go, telegraphing the end of the episode.
Yes.
That's okay.
You know, the Bible is not exactly a recent publication.
Yeah, yeah, I think people are red.
Reddit.
Maybe Sir Mark's not in as much detail, but yeah.
Not as much?
I mean, I've learned a lot.
Okay.
picking up now with verse 29.
But every name.
still made gods of its own and put them in the shrines of the high places that the Samaritans had made every nation in the cities in which they had lived the
Metababalon made Sukhas Benath the men of Kuth made Nurgle. It's my favorite name
The men of Hamas made the Warhammer 40k Nurgle
Really?
No, and the men of Babylon made Sukhas Benath the men of Kuth made Nurgle the men of Hamas made Ashima and the avides made Nibhaz and Tartak
and the Sepharvites burned their children in the fire to a Dremelek and Anamalek, the gods of Sepharvayim.
They also feared the Lord, and appointed from among themselves all sorts of people as priests of the high places,
who sacrificed for them and the shrines of the high places. So they feared the Lord, but also served their own gods after the manner of the nations, from among whom they had been carried away.
to this day they do according to the former manner.
They do not fear the
the Lord and they do not follow the statutes of the rules of the law or the commandments
of the Lord commanded the children of Jacob whom he named Israel. The Lord made a covenant
with them and commanded them, you shall not fear other gods or bow yourselves to them
or serve them or sacrifice to them, but you show fear of the Lord who brought you out
of the land of Egypt with great power with an outstretched arm. You show bow yourselves
to him and to him you show sacrifice and the statutes and the rules and the law and the
a commandment that he wrote for you,
you should always be careful to do
you should not fear other.
and you shall not forget the covenant that I made with you.
You shall not fear other gods,
but you shall fear the Lord your God,
and He will deliver you out of the hand of all your enemies.
However, they would not listen,
but they did according to their former manner.
So these nations feared the Lord
and also served their carved images.
Their children did likewise,
and their children's children, as their fathers did,
so they do to this day.
So notice the text almost sounds like it's contradicted itself.
Yeah.
Right?
So it says to this day they do a court of the former manor.
Oh no.
So first is so they fear the Lord, but also serve their own gods.
Yeah.
And then it says they do not fear the Lord.
They do not follow the same rule.
Yeah.
I mean, it's different definitions of that.
the idea is there's
sacrifice in the Yahweh, but also sacrificing other gods. But hey, remember Yahweh said,
don't sacrifice two other gods. But the, yeah, and so the important, but then after that again,
it says they feared the Lord, but they also serve the point being, the point being that
if you worship the Lord, but also worship other gods, you're not really worshiping the Lord.
Yep.
The true worship of God has exclusivity embedded in it.
From the very beginning, from the Torah being given to Moses, right?
Their exclusivity is built into it.
This has a lot of applications that we don't have time to go into tonight.
But exclusivity is a dirty word religiously in our modern scene.
But exclusivity is at the core of what Christianity has already been
have always been about throughout the history of the world.
Yeah, I mean, it's kind of job one.
It's commandment one.
Yes, there is the opposite of inclusiveness.
It's at the core of true religion.
Yeah.
So yeah, so this is describing
the initial phases of resettlement.
Right?
And so what are the reasons why we know it's hyperbole also is, what was the purpose of
moving all these people around?
So in part, the Assyrians would move people around like this to try to prevent rebellions.
Yeah.
So they're no longer connected to their ancestral land.
a kind of disposed of.
people more likely to fight to defend their own land than just some land. But there's
another piece to that because there's not just your identity in terms of you identifying
with the particular land. There's also your identity as a people. And so the Assyrians
also wanted to break and a big part of this resentment is the Assyrians trying to break
the identity of these people's
people's right. So they're deliberately trying to get people to enter Mary. Yeah. So they deliberately
left people there to intermarry with the people they were importing. Right. Because now these Babylonians
aren't going to end up being Babylonians anymore. Because they're going to intermarry with the other
groups and with the local former Israelites.
And the Israelites got to, yeah, as I say, they're not just trying to assimilate the Israelites.
They're also trying to assimilate these Babylonians and these other routes of people.
They want them to kind of merge and be a Syrians.
Right. They just have one identity as a Syrians for the whole empire.
Yeah. So this is because if you have a lot of intermarriage, people don't tend to keep
lots of distinct identities. They tend to merge like they fall apart.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
Yeah.
And we see this even on the level, right?
So I've mentioned before, I think, on the show,
that one of my former Old Testament professors,
Dr. Lawson Younger, spent a good chunk of his career
translating a bunch of previously untranslated
Assyrian tablets to track down exactly where all
of the quote-unquote Lawstripes of Israel went.
And he pretty much found the cities and villages
where they were sent.
Hmm.
by translating these tablets, how do you do that? People's names. Yeah, because they had Hebrew names,
right? That Hebrew, Israelite names. And that's true for a few generations. And then those names disappear.
From the city's records and from trade records and things. Why? Because they've intermarried. They've lost their Israelite identity.
Now, let me add another layer to this.
What is the easiest way to identify an ancient Near Eastern person based on their name?
The Semitic languages are all pretty close
That's true. I mean probably the easiest one would be to see what kind of Theophoric stuff this and that exactly tells you
Which got yeah, yeah, yeah, this wasn't in the notes by the way. I actually just guess correctly everybody
It's good with me
Because it wasn't in the briefing yesterday, you know?
Yeah, but yeah, nobody that makes sense, right?
Like like everyone's naming their kid, not everybody,
but a lot of people are naming their kids
with names that include the name of their god.
And it's your god that really kind of,
you know, is the distinction as to which
what group you are.
We were just talking about Jezebel.
Right? Has Bale, in her name.
Right. We were talking about Affleye.
I had you know, right?
And so that's the use of, and so a big part,
there is no
distinction between cult and culture at this point in history, right? And so part of breaking
down, this down is breaking down your allegiance to those ancestral gods. Yeah. Right. And that's
going to become important here when we get to the second half because what we've been presented here
in Second Kings is a certain picture of Samaritan religion, because now that's...
is where the Samaritan identity begins.
Right? So before the Syrians,
they would have been called themselves Israelites.
They were part of the nation of Israel.
Whose capital was Samaria?
Maybe the actual people who lived in Samaria
would have been referred to as Samaritans
like Jerusalemites or whatever it write,
or Parisians or parasites or whatever they call them in France.
Um, wow.
The,
Um.
So, right, but Samaritan is an identity comes out of this because it's the people living in the land of Samaria, which surrounds the city of Samaria, which is what the Assyrians call it now.
Just the people living there.
And so Samaritan identity becomes a new identity and our first picture here of Samaritan religion, right after the recital is that essentially you have this mix.
Yeah, right.
you have some Yahweh worship probably not very orthodox Yahweh worship. Right.
everything, right? But that's mixed with each of the groups that came there having brought their own
gods with them. But now, as they start to intermary and they start to mix and blend and develop
a Samaritan identity and a Samaritan culture, part of that is going to be a Samaritan religion that's
going to frankly involve all of them, yeah, giving up significant elements of what their past
source of plus.
and we will get into a little more of what that looks like in the second half.
Indeed. Alright, that's our first half of this episode on the Samaritans. We're gonna take a break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Just take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF Radio.
Poised between east and west, between Orthodox and Catholic, Lithuania, the last of Europe's
pagan nations, did not forget its ancient tales such as that of the giant esmeringa,
egglay queen of serpents, and the iron wolf.
Rather, they fulfilled and enriched them with legends like the hill of crosses and the
the miracle working.
icon of our Lady of the Gate of the Dawn.
In the Wolf and the Cross, Father Andrew Stephen Daymac and Deacon Sarifim Richard Roland
take a very personal pilgrimage into a land where history and legend have met and fused,
where Orthodox Christians have lived as a minority for nearly seven centuries.
Their faith founded upon the blood of martyrs and the witness of dozens of saints.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.inj
that is store.AncientFace.com
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Steven D'Young
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hey, we're back, everybody.
I know.
bumper Mike you're fired just kidding just kidding maybe that's okay we are back
it's the Lord of spirits are talking about that one job I know I know actually I
think that's the first time that that's happened or at least the first time I
could remember so I mean there's a hundred and forty episodes so that's pretty
good the call board is lighting up we have all these people calling in who knows
what it is they want to talk about multiple people from Texas.
Probably completely confused.
Thinking another completely confused.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
So yeah, who knows?
Who knows?
We'll see what's going on.
Poor Mike, he's just probably frantically pressing buttons.
You know, picking up the phone with one hand,
clicking the bumper with the other hand,
probably hitting something with his toe on his left foot.
You know, so that's all occurring.
So yeah, let's do that.
We got a camera there in the studio.
just
Mr. Tundin, so we can see what's going on there.
I just want to see everybody.
Everybody, I'm good to see the franticness.
Franticity, franticity.
Yeah, let's just take some calls.
Oh yeah, go ahead.
I was informed by a secret means
that there's a fellow,
Luterno alum in the YouTube chat.
Oh yes, yes, so much to say that.
So yes, it's the same doctor, loss, and younger.
Yeah, yeah.
Yes, congratulations.
You both have the same, had the same professor.
Um, yes. Yeah. May we may have met. Who knows? Oh, one of our occasional callers, a no says in the chat. He says, Father
Adieu since father Steven mentioned you joining a Southern mega church, you should start leading pilgrimages for trips to
Lithuania, just kidding, just kidding. Um, I mean, I will always go to Lithuania, but I'm not going with like a group.
I wonder if you're going to start doing zoom exorcisms and how much you'll charge.
That's true. I mean, if it's voice only, it'll be so much. If it's, if you actually want
to see my face, if you want me to touch the screen, that's going to be a little extra.
Yeah. So if they have to watch you do it, you should actually give them a discount.
That would. Oh, anyway. All right. Well, let's go ahead and take some calls. So, yeah,
We've got William, he says of Tennessee, but his phone says he's in
Wilmington North Carolina. So William, welcome, Laura Spirits podcast. Where are you really?
Tennessee. My phone is a liar. Oh, is your phone from North Carolina? Or it is, but much like a
Creighton, you can't trust what it says. Wow. Are you trying to use like a phone VPN to watch like
like Tongue in Netflix.
No, I got the stone in North Carolina, but I live in Tennessee.
Okay.
So you're back.
is all about the Polt pork but you're going on with the ribs. Is that what it's about?
Yes, although there are some wonderful replacements in North Carolina as well.
That is true. That is true. It's actually a good strategy though.
Here's why because most of the junk calls you get will be from the other area code.
That's true. Yes, but it's annoying when I call from them,
I think if I want to be pulled about some local political issues, that...
I have no connection to.
Block, block, block.
So William, what's on your mind tonight,
as we're talking about the Samaritans?
Well, speaking of the Samaritans,
the descendants of Ephraim and Intermarriage,
my question was on Osenov,
the wife of the patriarch Joseph,
which first is sort of,
pretty much to the question,
is Osenov considered a saint in the Orthodox Church?
because like she's name drops quite
positively in our first wedding service, but I'm not sure what date she is in the calendar.
Yeah, Joseph and Asnith, I don't know if she's a saint on the calendar. I know,
Joseph has a Cinexarian entry, but I don't think I can look this up real quick where we're talking.
I mean, it's a good question. Yeah, I mean, I literally had the Cinexarian right on hand here,
which is how I know that certain old test mode figures here.
not say it's just gonna rub that in for some people.
Let's see.
So that would be in December most likely because that's when all
those people are being commemorated.
Actually, I think Joseph is in what?
But anyway, well, so he gets commemorated during Holy week,
but not as like a cynic sorry and entry.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
Yeah, let's see.
Patriarch Joseph.
Yes, yes, you are.
He has an Egyptian headress.
Yes, yes, he does.
So yes, congratulations, Asinith.
She is commemorated on the Sunday.
Tt-t-t-t-t.
Yeah, the Sunday before the Nativity.
She is listed as the righteous
asnath the wife of Joseph, you know, cumley. Yep, yep. Yep. So there you go.
Saint asnath, you can get an icon of her, you know, painted absolutely a canonical
saint to the Orthodox Church. I have looked. It is very difficult to find an icon of her.
I might have to get you would have to get a commission. Yeah. Yeah. But in any case,
she has been a fascinating figure for me because well, she is Egyptian who married a Jewish
guy. And in previous episode, Jill talked about how Rachel was seen as the mother of the Jews,
iconographically Rachel leaping for her children and whatnot. I was wondering if,
Asuna, as the mother of Ephraim who became the largest tribe and had in her Gentile connection,
and if that has gentile
the same way that Rachel was, or even mother of the Samaritan,
and the same way Rachel was considered the mother of the Jews.
I don't think so. I mean, usually like the thing you are as the thing
you're dead is.
I mean, I think that's the thing that's the thing that's the thing that's the same
way that Rachel was, or even mother of the Samaritan,
I don't think so. I mean usually like the thing you are as the thing your dad is.
Yeah. You know, at this point, yeah, yeah, changes the Judaism later. Yeah. Yes, yes, of course, of course. Yeah.
But yeah, the fact that Joseph, you know, that's sorry, that Manasson F from our sons of Joseph, that's what they are.
You know, well, yeah, their main identity. So, so the Rachel thing and this is going to come up later.
uh, uh, teaser, um, like that very
You quoted it's gonna come up here in a little bit
Rachel was considered the mother of all of Israel
And
This is another one of those things of Ephraim's kind of standing Ephraim kind of standing in for all of Israel
Yeah, because she was of course actually Joseph's mother
right so it's a little different right it's it's
Rachel is sort of the mother, really grandmother, but mother of Ephraim.
And in texts that are treating Ephraim as synonymous with Israel, she is therefore treated
as the mother of Israel.
The other thing with Asinath is starting in the second temple period, but this really
flowers, shall we say, in the rabbinic Judaism.
So, when you get to, we mentioned how things change, so things are reckoned matrilineally
in Judaism.
Yeah.
That starts changing after the exile.
Think about Ezra and the prohibition against marrying foreign women, right?
So that becomes an issue.
And so in response to that, you start to see this development of the tradition that flowers
and rabbinic Judaism where they try to make ass-
and if not Egyptian. Are you ready for how?
Confirm that she, uh, Joseph's niece?
Yes. There's a midrash. Oh, that, uh, when the man of Shekham forced themselves on Dina,
Joseph sister, she became pregnant.
Wow.
And the baby was left.
on the walls of Egypt. Now I don't think Egypt actually has like
walls around the country but you get the point. The baby was abandoned somewhere in your Egypt.
Baby is adopted. I think maybe they were going for like a Moses typology thing, right?
This will have baby adopted by Egyptians.
becomes the adopted daughter of that Egyptian priest.
And then Mary's, Mary's just...
and that gets them around him having a non-Israelite wife. Now it causes a bigger problem because
Levinicus 18, you're not allowed to marry your niece. Yeah, right. So that explanation has its own
problems. But yeah, so that was in Jewish circles. Whereas when you read like Joseph and Asana,
these texts that were super popular in early Christianity.
very quickly she becomes an image of the Gentile Church.
Yeah.
And sort of the romance between them is seen as sort of a story that's about conversion.
Right.
It's sort of if we're thinking of the church as the bride of Christ,
then romance would be sort of Christ converting wooing.
the soul, right? It's that kind of dynamic in early Christian thought regarding acid.
Yeah. All right. Well, thank you very much. That's a great question. And I can't believe I
had never bothered to look up where their azanith was actually commemorated as a saint before,
but now I'm very happy to learn that she is. So it's good. It's good. I thank you. I love
the title, St. Joseph, the all
He is renowned throughout the history of the church for looks maxing.
Well, I mean, if you read Joseph and the acid it's right like the text basically she's like, wow, this wow.
You know, like that's the whole thing. She's just impressed by his all-comeliness.
Okay, we're going to take at least one more call here.
So we've got Isaac calling from Loveland, Colorado. Isaac, welcome to the Lord of Spheres podcast.
Good afternoon, fathers.
As someone with a with
a phone number in a different state than where I live.
I can vouch it is great for spamming.
Don't call it.
It's one of the easiest ways to slow it that out.
So you're in Loveland.
Are you perhaps connected with Father Evans Church out there?
Oh, yeah.
I think I was father Evan quite a bit.
Just a flat patient with him when I can.
You got a fun therapist up here growing quite a bit.
Well, tell them I said hello and calm down.
I'm just I'm just I didn't say his life.
There could be a hundred Isaacs at that church.
You know, probably not as many as high UC Osis and porphyryosis and serifims as we as we all have these days, but
Teacones, yeah, you know, yeah, yeah, well, that's in the OCA
We do have we've got more serifims than Isaacs, but there are at least six Isaacs
Well, there you go. So you're just just one of six. Yeah, so what's what's me? What's out your bio Isaac?
So I'm curious.
It would seem as though that the displacement of the 12 tribes is the
result of them not being faithful to God.
And I guess I'm trying to sort that with the idea that like I guess you guys said the
punishment was hyperbolic when it says that you know they were all gone, they were all
killed.
Then the idea being that they were you know the text is being hyperbolic and well how
much I'm trying to say this.
And so much as the 12 tribes were unfaithful.
that many were displaced or killed or punished.
And that trying to settle that with the idea of
you know that Christianity is a maybe not so individualistic as it was when I was raised
in a Protestant background but more communal in that we were saved in relationships yet.
It would seem as though perhaps if you know there was a Jew in the 12 tribes that was not unfaithful,
would they still have been punished for the
unfaithfulness of their community and their tribe.
Yeah, yeah. So what do you think, Father? I mean, what's, yeah, I mean, functionally,
functionally yes. Right. Functionally, right? Not it isn't like, you know, the deportees
were individually
less evil than the people who were killed by the Assyrians, for example, right?
Like on an individual sorting out basis, right? The blessings of God came upon
the whole nation, right? He brought them all out of Egypt, right? Brought all of
their descendants, right, to the land and gave them all the land. Some of them were
or righteous, some of them were wicked, right?
And then...
The wickedness right the collective wickedness begins to tip the scale that doesn't mean there was not a single person right at the time of
Elijah remember he dispares he's like I'm the only one left in the northern kingdom who still yeah worships you and God says there's 10,000
I would bow the need to bail right so that there is this faithful remnant there but when
When devastation comes upon the country the nation in terms of you know
Who wins?
up having individual things happen to them. I mean, that gets that gets shared across
across everybody just like, you know, Jeremiah suffers a whole lot. He's the faithful
prophet at the time that Jerusalem is, you know, falling to the Babylonians. But he still
gets thrown down a well and he's stuck it right. And so this is part of the understanding
of what happens in the resurrection and the final judgment.
Right, is that looking at individual earthly lives and even sometimes collectives, depending
on how big of a collective you look at earthly lives, you don't always see justice in that
span.
Yeah.
Right?
You see this in the Psalms, there are wicked people who prosper, right, and go to their
graves fat and happy.
Right, and there are righteous people who's
suffer their whole lives and that life is all too short. Right? And so this is why the
last judgment, right, is a promise. A lot of the times when it's talked about in the
Old Testament. Right? A rise of God had judged the earth. This is something we want to
happen. Right? God established justice. Because if you're somebody who has received
injustice in this life.
right? And that's a promise. That's a hopeful thing that God is going to establish justice.
The reason we fear the last judgment is because somewhere deep in our soul, we know that,
hey, I might be on the wrong side of this, right? I don't know that I'm one of the righteous people who's getting oppressed and suffering.
I kind of feel like I have it pretty good.
And I do more than my share of synonyms, right?
So.
For us, we look at it with fear because there's something tickling at the back of our head going, you need to straighten some things out to prepare for this, right?
And that is the idea of what Scripture tells us that if you judge yourself, you will not be judged.
Right, if I get things right in my own life through repentance, right, and faithfulness,
then I don't have to fear the day.
I stand before the judgment seat of Christ. Then that will become a promise for me and
not a threat. But that requires me to make some things right on my own beforehand.
Because if not, anything that's left dangling, Christ is going to make it right on that day.
Yeah.
Does that help out Isaac?
Does that make things a little more clear?
Yeah, definitely. That helps out a bunch. Appreciate it.
Thanks. Excellent. Excellent. Thanks for calling. Okay. We're going to take one more call
before we roll on with the second half here and we've got Paul calling from Texas.
So Paul, welcome to the Lord's Pierce podcast. Thank you very much, Father. It's Christ
in the Senate. I can't remember what this, it's not a common greeting, you know.
Neither can I. I was hoping you all would educate me. I know the truth is here's the truth.
the hard truth that a lot of I don't I don't
go with for those orthodoxy in America don't want a face which is Christ is risen as the singular universal
festival greeting and then kind of you know a decent showing for Christ is born and the others
it's fine you know but but they're not a lot of people are not even going to know them you know
you could kind of just respond to all of them with he is it ever shall be right there you go
because that's technically true.
There's a little greeting creep going on, I think.
You know what I'm saying?
He's risen and always shall be. He's born and always shall be. He's in our midst. He always shall be. He could be here's a spicy take. He could be just like those Greeks who come to church once a year and they always just say, oh,
for everything. Anyway, so yes, so Paul, what's on your mind?
Okay, so I had a, of course, like I normally do, I have a question and then kind of a bonus question if there's time, but it does relate the second question.
has to do with justice which has to do with the populaces, it seems to be at least.
But the first one, we've touched on this before in old, much older, I think,
podcast where we've talked about the idea, and y'all touched on it even here, of course, that the idea
of a people, a people groups identity is more caught within their religio, like that would unite them.
More than like the idea of ethnicity or anything like that, or even necessarily the idea of like
like being tied to the land, which you'll definitely
catch on the past like 30 minutes.
I want to know when assuming it happened before the Enlightenment,
it could just have been after the Enlightenment for all I know.
Assuming it happened before the Enlightenment,
I want to know when that kind of thing started to shift,
because that's so hard for modern people to get now.
The idea is that basically,
because more or less,
that almost says the identity of a people
was identified with who they worshipped.
But even that can get muddy when you're looking at it with
Agons and how they would have a little bit of
So to speak with my god friends and look at the wrong
Romans and Greeks that have, you know, the, what is it?
Saturn and Zeus or is that Jupiter, but or Mars and Aries and all that stuff.
Like there seems to be a bit of overlap and it gets kind of confusing.
So I wanted to notice how that kind of developed into what it has become now with like it being,
you know, ethnicity, so to speak.
Yeah.
I mean, my sense is that, um, that there's a couple of shatterings of that concept.
one of them of course.
of course, is frankly comes in the wake of the Reformation, where, as I recall, like the
first European country to try to come up with some way for, like, let's all just get
along kind of approach to religion to some extent.
Was Prussia where you've got both Lutherans, and I think it's Lutherans that are reformed
that are both present there.
And they're like, well, because I, is I recall, like, one of the kings and his wife where
they were on different sides of this question.
And so he's like, well, let's just come up with one Prussian Church that kind of became
incorporate both these things.
And we'll just, you know, we'll do it all.
And so gradually you get the sense of religion being this private thing.
And it's okay for everybody who lives in an area to belong to different religions, different
churches, whatever.
And so then, well, what is it that binds you together?
Well, we're all Prussians here.
You know, that kind of sense of a localized identity, a national...
identity. I mean, this is when you get the emergence of the nation state, right? Because before that,
there really isn't that kind of thing in the world. So I think that's part of it, but, you know,
the enlightenment is also an issue there too, right? Where you get people where, you know, religious
identity is just getting stripped away entirely. And so then people are looking for kind of a
scientific basis for identity. So ethnicity often people talk about ethnicity in terms of
of DNA and stuff now, even though...
ethnicity, I mean the word is from ethnos, meaning a nation or a people originally wouldn't have had
that sense and still even kind of technically ethnicity is not necessarily your genetics because
like what you inherit genetically is not simply the sum of all of your ancestors. Like, you know,
genes drop out every generation. You don't contain DNA from every single one of your ancestors,
right but you have a sense of okay I'm you know like I'll say I'm Lithuanian the truth is
is that only a sliver of me genetically speaking is Lithuanian. There's a bunch of other stuff mixed in there as well.
But that's the sort of ethnicity that my family kind of sort of remembers even though we weren't raised with that culture.
But yeah, I think that's a lot of where I would put it. I mean, there's still many places in the world where everybody belongs to the same religion.
And so a sense of this is just what everybody does and everybody, who everybody is, I think that still is present in a lot of places.
And indeed when we talk we're gonna talk
towards the end of this half about modern Samaritans,
and they are definitely classified by a lot of groups
as a lot of scholars as a quote,
ethno religion, meaning that, you know,
if you belong to that people, you belong to that religion,
if you can't belong to that religion,
if you're not part of that people, you know,
you're born into it and that's just kind of the way
that it is, and it's defined by what they do as a group.
So I mean, that's my sense of it.
I don't know, Father.
what-what-what-what-what-what-What are you-What are you-What are you...
What do you think? Yeah. Well, to give some more detail, I think so what you're talking about in Prussian stuff comes out in the wake of the 30 years war. Right. Right.
Like, plus, not just the war of religious Protestants and Catholics and
other groups of Protestants killing each other.
Why have you got about a third of the population of Europe in the process and just causing massive destruction? And so a lot of things emerge out of that in terms of
history of ideas. You get sort of classical foundationalism that's going to form part of the enlightenment out of that. The idea that we need to base
societal structures and civic life on something that is objective and therefore that we all have in common.
Right. That it's some kind of objective, even mathematical rational reality, rather than basing our society around religion.
in general, right?
that pursue ultimately doesn't work, but I'll get to that in a second. The best example, though, is not actually a form of Christianity in Prussia, it's what happens to Judaism in Prussia.
Because in Europe, even more than the different types of Christianity.
that become associated with different city states and nation, you know, newly forming nations and
princes, etc. The Jewish people in Europe were because they had this identity as a people
that incorporated their religious identity.
They were...
functionally separate no matter where they were, they were Jews and no matter what
country they happened to be living in and they were therefore not really part of
whatever the other people was that right if they're in France they're not part
of the French people right if they're in pressure they're part of the
pressure people the Polish people they're not polls right they're not Frenchman
they're not right and so the deliberate effort there was that actually I mean
And this is a thing.
that was negotiated was the idea that Jews would be a loud freedom of religion within the
Prussian state provided they saw it moved to seeing themselves as Prussians and not Jews.
They were Prussians who practiced the religion of Judaism, just like they were Prussians who
practiced, you know.
who were practicing Lutherans or reformed or Roman Catholics or whatever, right?
But Prussian came first and that's where reformed Judaism was born.
Reform Judaism was born out of the people who accepted the compromise.
The Jews who did not are what we now know as Orthodox Jews,
for whom their identity as a people and their religion are still tied immediately together.
But so that the
And then, as Father Andrew,
it gets kind of transferred to the nation state.
Rather, it's something actual objective
and rational and scientific.
It gets transferred to the nation state,
which is basically the application of force.
And the idea of a people is ingrained into human nature.
Because humans are unable to live alone.
We're social creatures. We're social animals, right?
And so we need to have, we have a sense of our people beginning with our family, our extended family, right, our people.
And so anything that tries to erode that once that sense is established ends up not working.
And this is why nationalism has only worked historically when...
that nationalism basically the line is drawn around to people.
So for example, France.
Right.
The borders of France basically surround the French people.
England, it works fine.
The borders of England surround the English people.
The United Kingdom has had some problems.
I don't know if you know about this.
I've heard that.
Because the line is that line is drawn around the Irish people, the Scottish people, the English people, the Welsh people, right, who all have their own sense of identity as a people.
Right. This is why Yugoslavia didn't work.
This is why Arab nationalism largely hasn't worked.
Right.
I mean, Iraq is disintegrated.
right as soon as the power that was trying to force all those different people
groups to be together as a nation went away. And I'll add, and this will make a bunch of people mad,
but one of the reasons why it's going to be so long before we have an American Orthodox
Church is that there's not an American people. It's true. And the reason there's not an American people,
I mean, there's a whole ton of problems, right?
But we can't even decide how that would be constant.
When you look at nationalist movements in the United States, they have always tried to
define the American people as some subset of the American people.
And not only as some subset, but some subset from somewhere else.
So the early, very earliest nationalist movements, it was Anglo-Saxon people.
Then it got loosened up to northern Europeans.
Now it's loosened up most nationalists in the US.
now it's Europeans. Those are the real American people. Well, okay, so there's a whole pile
soon to be most of the people living in America who aren't in that category. Number one,
number two, that's a people that's not from America, that's a people from somewhere else.
And number three, when you draw a line around Europe, you're including like
like dozens of different peoples.
Yeah, there is no European cult.
And trust me, look at the EU. Any attempt to have a European government would fail because they kind of tried that with the EU at least at a low level and it's failed miserably.
Right. So yeah, until there's a sense, until the people who live in the United States of America have a sense of themselves as A people.
And some kind of unity.
around something. You can't have an American Orthodox Church because you can't have an
expression of Orthodox Christianity that is an expression of the American people because
there's not an American people. Yeah. Yep. I don't know. I hope that that's helpful. Pauline
doesn't muddy the waters too much. It's obviously it's a huge huge question with lots of different
rabbit trails that one could go.
down, you know, of course, but yeah.
Yeah, I appreciate it, Father.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, thanks very much for calling.
All right.
Roland, was failure.
Vogue, treaty of West failure.
No, no reference to the treaty of Versailles this time.
No, no.
I've said enough.
All right.
Yes.
OK.
All right.
So at the end of the first half,
we basically get some maritons as a people.
There we go.
coming onto the scene, you know, this kind of merging together, yeah, merging together
of these different pagan groups, but then also there's Yahweh worship going on as well.
So then we have Samaritan. So what's up with those Samaritans? So they became a side felt
they got a new. Yes, exactly. Who are these people? Hockey 80 standup. I didn't. There you
up with elevators. Why do I keep pushing the button?
Those are coming faster.
Okay, so,
well, so part of what happens is,
is historically Samaria, right?
Whenever the Assyrian project was,
Assyrian doesn't last all that long.
And it's overthrown by Babylon,
and then the Babylonian empire doesn't last that long.
And then we come under the Persians.
And then under the Persians, Samaria.
becomes a province, a satrap.
And then becomes a province under the Greek cell, you kids.
It's for a time a province under a Rome and then it gets merged.
But we'll talk about that in a little bit.
But so whatever that original project was of the Assyrians in Samaria,
that project obviously kind of falls by the wayside, right?
and the land and the people there come under this series of dominions.
But the other thing that happens in the midst of this is, of course,
Judah Falls, the exile happens to Babylon.
And so there's 70 years there where the Samaritan people,
Right, we've now had...
few generations of intermarriage and this kind of thing happening. They now, their land
starts to extend into a little bit into what was Judah, right, in terms of where people
are living and this kind of thing. And then under the Persians, Cyrus allows the people
of Judah to return, many of which do.
And they get ready to...
Not all, not all.
That's why Persian Jews left, yes.
Yes, yes.
And Mr. Damien, yeah, that's why there's a Babylonian Talmud.
Yes.
So the province, the area we're talking about, right,
for most of this period.
So the period before Christ, basically.
So the 500 years that we're talking about here,
We're basically talking about the area north of Judah, south of Galilee, between the Mediterranean
and the Jordan.
And that region was incredibly fertile, in terms of groves of fruit trees, planting crops,
because it got a lot of rain coming off of the Mediterranean.
so
economically, this greatly benefits the Samaritan people because they're growing food to feed
not only themselves but the neighboring provinces. And when you have imperial infrastructure,
especially once you get to the Romans and you've got Roman roads, but even with the Greeks,
as these as these successive empires build more and more infrastructure, they're able to
carry that food, the produce of the land of Samaria, north, south, down towards Egypt, right?
different places, spurs, economic activity and growth, plus you have trade routes that
trade routes that pass through Samaria on their way to Egypt and other point south, and then
on their way north up into the fertile crescent, up into Asia Minor, what's now Turkey.
So it's a prosperous area, but the Samaritans who are there.
Now coming into an identity as a people and starting to thrive, when these Judahites come back
to form the province of Judea and start building the city of Jerusalem and especially building
city walls around Jerusalem, they get a little nervous. And that nervousness produces an episode
that's recorded in the book of Ezra,
there.
that is going to be sort of a flashpoint
from the Jewish perspective in terms of
tension and enmity between these two peoples.
Yeah.
So looking at Ezra, chapter four, beginning with verse seven.
In the days of Artexerxes.
So that's the Persian king, right?
Bishlam and Mithradath and Tobiel
and the rest of their associates
Root to RxRxc's king of...
Persia. The letter was written in Aramaic and translated.
Rehum the commander and Shimshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to Ardok
Srixis the king as follows. Rehum the commander Shimshai the scribe and the rest of their
associates, the judges, the governors, the officials, the Persians, the men of Eric,
the Babylonians, the men of Susa, that is the Ilamites, and the rest of the nations who
the great and noble Osnafar deported and settled in the cities of Samaria, and in the rest
So the province beyond the
river. This is a copy of the letter that they sent. Two art exorcces the king, your servants,
the men of the province beyond the river, send greeting. And now be it known to the king that the
Jews who came up from you to us have gone to Jerusalem. They are rebuilding that rebellious and
wicked city. They are finishing the walls and repairing the foundations. Now be it known to the
king that if the city is rebuilt and the walls finished, they will not pay tribute, custom, or toll,
and the Royal Revenue will be in
Now, because we eat the salt of the palace, and it is not fitting for us to witness the King's dishonor,
therefore we send and inform the King.
In order that search may be made in the book of the records of your fathers,
you will find in the book of the records and learn that this city is a rebellious city,
hurtful to kings and provinces, and that sedition was stirred up in it from a void.
That was why the city was laid waste.
We make known to the king that if the city's rebuilt and its walls finished
You will then have no possession of the province beyond the river.
So, uh,
yeah, so
they're concerned, right, that
And these are the people, right, these are gonna be the Judeans from which we get the term Jews
So this is the beginning of people who would identify as Jews, right?
Yeah, in our parlance and
Now we have the Samaritans have this sense of identity to the north of them
They are threatened by the returning Jews and by
their establishment of fortifications, right?
And so they send this letter for their concern.
And basically, right?
So you know about the salt if you've seen 300, right?
This is part of how you submitted to Persia
that to do with the salt.
The base is they look, we're loyal vassals.
We love you guys.
You guys are the best, best emperor ever.
And we're totally loyal and faithful.
And so because of that, we just want to warn you,
Like this.
There's a reason this city got wiped out by a nebukinizer.
These people are a problem.
They cause trouble.
They're not going to submit to your authority.
There'd be nothing but trouble.
They're going to have an insurrection.
They say, your servant's the men of the province beyond the river.
And they end it with, if you let them finish their walls, you'll have...
No, probably the other river they're basically singling they're gonna take us over right? That's the person
They're gonna establish their big kingdom. Yeah, they're gonna try to reestablish their whole kingdom here
And to seed them rebuilding this stuff is step one
Right, you can't you can't trust these guys
Yeah
All right picking up with verse 17
The king sent an answer
Jurei, whom the commander and chim se the scribe, the rest of their associates who live in
Samaria and in the rest of the province.
beyond the river, greeting.
And now, the letter that you sent to us has been plainly read before me, and I made it
to create, search has been made, and it has been found that the city from of old has
risen against kings, and that rebellion and sedition have been made in it.
And mighty kings have been over Jerusalem who ruled over the whole province beyond the
river, to whom tribute, custom, and toll were paid.
Therefore, make it to create that these men be made to cease and that the city be not rebuilt,
until it to create is made by me.
take care not to be select
in this matter. Why should damage grow to the her to the king? Then when the copy of King
Ardick's Seerix's letter was read, before Rahum and Shimshay the scribe and their associates,
they went and haze to the Jews at Jerusalem and by force and power made them cease,
and the work on the house of God that is in Jerusalem stopped and it ceased until the second year
of the reign of Darius, King of Persia. You don't want to be British and pronounce that Darius?
Darius. Yes.
like constant time.
Yeah, and so the letter works.
Right.
Yeah.
And everybody's back.
It says, yeah, let's just shut this down.
Don't I say otherwise, right?
Better safe than sorry.
And so it gets shut down.
And so this begins.
So what we're seeing in Ezra here,
this is from the Jewish perspective.
This is the beginning of enmity.
Right.
towards their northern neighbors. So what happens then and the the
judaites, right, return to SouthJudia, around 515 BC. So we're getting into the
beginning of the fifth century now. As eventually, right, the Jerusalem is rebuilt
and then eventually the temple is rebuilt in Jerusalem.
There is sort of a reaction going on
among the Samaritan people.
So they as a people are now sort of reforming
their group identity.
Yeah, under right because now at this point.
They don't remember, oh, this family was brought here from Babylon and this family is descended from Israelites and that family.
It's been a long time.
It's all been intermarried.
Right. And so they're forming their identity as well.
They're the successor of the kingdom of Judah.
We are the successor of the northern kingdom of Israel.
Yeah. Right.
And just as they are now saying
they are the real heirs of the Torah
and everything about it, right?
And beginning to say, and you,
Samaritans are not, right?
The Samaritans do essentially the same move.
Yeah.
The Samaritans say, no, we are the real heirs of the Torah.
We are the sons of Joseph.
We are the sons of Ephraim.
You guys are not, right?
And so as a second temple is built in Jerusalem, the Samaritan's build, what they consider to be in the fifth century around the same time, what they consider to be the real second temple.
And that temple is built on Mount Gharism.
And they are going to point at things.
Historically in the Torah and in the book of Joshua and other things to argue that Judah and Benjamin were always
Not great people
They were always the problematic ones not the northern kingdom
There's a southern kingdom that was that was the issue. They have their temple now at Mount Gharism
They begin a high priesthood
That is headquartered at Shechem
Yep.
And if you remember, uh, in the Old Testament before the taking of Jerusalem, the tabernacle
was at Chechem, right?
So that was the place of worship.
It's where the high priest, like Eli, lived, right?
He's going to come up again.
Yes.
Uh, multiple times.
Yeah.
That's maybe.
Um, but so there's a high priest at Chechem.
And so, obviously that the
Samarins have no political independence whatsoever at this time.
Right.
To the Persians or anytime for a long time.
Frankly.
Yeah.
They never get political independence really.
And so they don't have a political leader.
They're governed by a governor from Persia slash the cell.
You could slash Rome, right?
Slash.
Mostly Rome.
Then later, they're very assaulting it's.
they do have
a high priest. And so that high priest is sort of the leader of the people, right? The
Samaritan people look to leadership. Their culture is led by, and this sort of their
bar, their leadership as a people with an identity is that high priest at check him. Who is
the one who is the high priest at the temple on Mount Gharism? Right? And so, check him is,
and the area around that garrison become
the
the religious center and the center of the people's identity while Samaria had been rebuilt
as a city and that's where the provincial governors were, right?
That was the center of civil government for whoever the imperial government was at the
time was at the city of Samaria.
But that's why we have, you may never have thought about this, but when we get to like
the New Testament and stuff, they're the Samaritans, but Samaria is not all that important to
as a people, because that's just the government center and it's not their government.
Yeah.
Is it right?
So the heartland for them is Mount Garesum, check them, right?
This area, not the city of Samaria per se.
Central to both their identity as a people and the function.
of this religion, right, of this religious practice, which is worshiping Yahweh, the God of Israel,
at this temple on Mount Gharism. Yeah. And it seems like that the idolatrous bits have kind of fallen
away by this point. Yes. Yes. Yeah. So this is the religion that gives an identity to this
American people as such, right? Yeah. Not the fractured different religions they were practicing before
they really came together to have collective identity as a people.
And so that the core of that is their version of the Torah, what we now call the Samaritan
Pentateuch usually, like in scholarship when they refer to the text.
And for them, this is the, those five books, their Torah, this is the canonical scripture.
They don't.
Yes, it's the whole.
Like they have a version, they have a version of the book of Joshua Wright, but they
regarded as kind of like
Protestants would macabees like oh, interesting historical, you know, whatever, but it's not scripture.
Yeah. Yeah. Nothing else is on the level of the Torah for them at all, even close to it.
Yeah, there are other ancient historical texts and that kind of thing. But
and sort of their perspective that means they can easily say those contain errors, right?
Yeah. Or biases. Yeah. Because they don't have any Jewish biases, right?
They don't have any...
taken in those texts, you know?
Yeah, and so the the original of the Samaritan Pentateuch of their Torah was in Hebrew, but the very earliest
Kyiv's ever written in a Samaritan script. So the letters you see, the alphabet letters you see when you look at
a Hebrew Bible today or even that modern Hebrew uses are aromatic block letters.
that those
are no round. Right? That's how we're talking about. So early biblical manuscripts are in what's
called Paleo Hebrew. That's the script. Right. That's the way of writing the letters. There is a
Samaritan script. And that Samaritan script was used both for the Samaritan Hebrew dialect and for
air maic in some cases. Yeah, and you can look this up. It's really interesting to look at. You
You just see pictures of it on the internet.
Yeah.
But we have translations of it, ancient translations of it, I should say, and some of them for reasons that we're going to talk about here into Aramaic, right?
Which you'd expect in the Persian period because Aramaic is the imperial Aramaic is the language of the Persian Empire and then Greek and then Aramaic.
When you look at the Samaritan Pentateuch, the reason it gets talked about most of the
often like in the US, right, is primarily when you're doing
text criticism in biblical studies. So the Samaritan
Pentateuch, it has its own little Gothic font letter that you
get in text critical apparatuses or apparatus in books. So when
You compare it with the Maseratic text.
with short of today's standard Hebrew of the Torah.
Right? There are 6,000 differences.
That seems like a lot.
You say holy cow, right?
But or great, googly,
but most of those,
sort of like when you hear how many text, you know,
you hear a friend of the show, Bart Irman say,
there are more text variants in the New Testament
that there are words in the New Testament.
And you go, wow, how can that even be?
Most of these are very minor, right?
Yeah, like spelling, slight grammar differences.
Spelling grammar, conjugation.
And part of that is dialectic, meaning, right,
like the Hebrew of the Maseratic text of the Torah
and the Hebrew and Arabic used by the Samaritan.
are different dialects. So as you can imagine, different dialects spell words a little differently
or use certain words a little differently or phrase things a little differently. That's
most of it, okay, of the 6,000. The vast majority. Interestingly, when you compare it with
the septuogen, the Samaritan penituk and the septuogen. And this is the actual septuogen because
We're talking about the first five books. We're talking about the talk.
There you go.
Or in their case, the only five books.
Yeah.
So, we know now, for sure, I mean, people hypothesize this for a long time, but we now know
for absolute certain because of the Dead Sea Scrolls that the Septuagint Greek is translated
from a different Hebrew text than the Maseretic text tradition.
Yeah.
But there were at least those two Hebrew texts that existed side by side, right?
What became the maseritic text and what was translated in degree can became the Septuagint.
So when we're comparing the Septuagint, we're trying to figure out, well, we're really
trying to figure out because it's two different languages.
Compare that to the Sermon Pettituk.
trying to figure out how close the Hebrew Vorlaga, the Hebrew original behind the
the septuogen translation was how close that Hebrew was to the Samaritan penitut.
And what we find is that 2,000 of those 6,000 variants, so about a third, and 6,000 in 2000,
in this case, by the way, are both round numbers.
It's not exactly 6,000 or exactly 2,000.
So roughly a third of the variants between the maseritic text and the septuogen, or maseric
text of the Samaritan Pentateuch are shared by the Septuagint.
So the Samaritan Pentateuch and the Septuagint agree with each other over against the Maseratic
text.
Yeah.
And in many, yeah, again, it mostly doesn't matter, but it's interesting, you know, that
there's this overlap.
It's kind of a Venn diagram.
Right.
Well, here's why I think it matters.
Here's why I think it matters.
It shows that...
There is a family tree of Hebrew manuscripts, right?
And maybe Hebrew manuscript traditions.
Yeah.
Even though we don't have too much of it.
Number one, it shows us that the Samaritan penituk
is not just someone taking the Torah from the Maseretic
text and fiddling with it, which
was I had
hypothesis for a long time, right? Was that basically the Samaritans took the Torah, that the
Torah that existed at the time in the fifth century BC looked pretty much exactly like the
Maseretic Torah, and the Samaritans took it and just deliberately changed things and
with it, right? This is evidence that that's not the case, right? That's some of the
of at least a third of those variants for the Maseradek text are based on already existing
Hebrew variants. And it also is further evidence that one of the old theories about the septuagint
that it's basically a bad translation of the Maseradek Hebrew is also false.
Right, that it's more evidence that it's based on a different Hebrew original that was in
In.
circulation and that elements of that found itself in both the Samaritan
Pentateuch and in
Septurgy.
So, yeah, so we've got those variants that are shared. We said most of them are very
minor. What are some of the interesting and important ones? Okay, so I'm pretty
sure it's been on this show.
I talked too much in too many different places so I never remember what I said
right, but I know in whole Council of God, the Deuteronomy 5 and Exodus 20, and I'm pretty
sure at some point on the show, we've talked about the 10 commandments or the 10 words,
and the fact that one of the really interesting things about them is that there aren't 10, right,
right? They're actually like just grammatically in the text, there are nine. Nevertheless, even though
So you only get 9 things grammatically out of the...
text, everyone is always referred to it as the 10 words or the 10 commandments.
Yeah.
And so historically, different groups have split one of the nine into two in different ways,
or incorporated another piece of the text as a tenth one.
So, and rabbinic Judaism does that one way, or that Oxychiani does that one way, Roman Catholicism
and Lutheranism do that one way.
form.
Protestant tradition does that another way.
So there are different ways to divide them to get to a tent.
So the Samaritan Pettitouk takes a different approach.
They just add a tenth one.
So they use the grammar to say, well, here's nine,
and then they add a tenth one.
And the tenth one that they add is all sacrifices
have to take place on Mount Gharism.
Okay. That one looks like it's deliberate change. Right? It's hard to imagine how that was
just a text variant that they found. They got left out of literally everything else. Yeah.
Yeah, but, but before we write off just, oh, okay, they're just changing everything.
to make their temple legit. Yeah, a little bit more to think about. And this is one of the
really interesting things to me, but I'm a nerd. So your mileage may vary. But well, I
mean, why did people tune into this show? This has to do with Deuteronomy 27 versus 4 through
7. And what Father Andrew is about to read is basically what you will find in pretty
much.
any English Bible that you look up Deuteronomy 27 verses 4 through 7.
Okay. And when you have crossed over the Jordan, you shall set up these stones concerning which I
command you today on Mount Ebal and you shall plaster them with plaster and there you shall build
an altar to the Lord your God and altar of stones. You shall wield no iron tool on them. You
You shall build an altar to the Lord your God of uncultiv-
stones and you shall offer burnt offerings on it to the Lord your God and you
shall sacrifice peace offerings and shall eat there and you shall rejoice before
the Lord your God. Right, so that all sounds normal, right? This is when there's
right near not right at but near the end of Deuteronomy and Moses is telling
the people, hey when you cross the Jordan you come to Mount Ebal you put these
standing.
stones there, you build an altar there and offer thanks to God there. You offer sacrifice
there. This is going to be the first altar that gets built in the land of Canaan, right?
In the Promised Land after they cross Georgia. But here's the interesting thing. As you
might expect, right, you probably get to anticipate, I'm going to tell you that in the Samaritan
pentatook in the cement pentatook.
when you read these verses, it doesn't say Mount Ebal, it says Mount Garrism, which is
right next to Mount Ebal.
Which you'd expect given their sort of preference for baptism.
That's where they're getting exactly.
So you could say, oh, okay.
So this is then, you know, changing it up so that this first alter that gets built to
the Promised Land is built on Mount Garrism to justify them having their temple and worshiping
there.
But
One of the very important scrolls we found among the Dead Sea Scrolls is 4Q Dute.
Yes, that's the reference.
Yes, the Dute is for Duteronomy.
That's right.
It is a scroll of the Book of Duteronomy.
And 4Q Dute is found in the 4th cave.
Right.
4th cave.
Fork you do is the
Deuteronomy scroll where it has preserved in Deuteronomy 32 that when God divided the nations,
He divided them according to the number of the sons of God. Which was very important because
that explained why in the Septuogen it said he numbered them according to the number of his angels.
The Maseretic text says, according to the number of the sons of Israel.
Right, so...
In that place in Deuteronomy, it records this older reading that had been shifted in the
Maseretic tradition.
That older reading was also testified to by the Greek.
Right?
Well, do you look at that Dead Sea Scroll of Deuteronomy 27?
Instead of Mount E. Ball, it says Mount Garesum.
So basically the dead sea scrolls agrees with the Samaritan,
Pentora
on this point. Yes, which means in this case, this may have actually been changed by the Jews.
Because the Samaritans were pointing at it, not vice versa.
We don't know, but it's interesting. Yes, yes. At the very least, the Samaritans did not change it.
The Samaritans were pointing at something that they found there in the text, right?
Whether why the BASEREDIC doesn't reflect that, yes, that is the subject of conjecture.
And then in general, another feature you see that accounts for a bunch of the variants
is that we've talked before on the show when we were talking about Old Testament Christology
when we did those episodes.
We talked about how like a
of Aramaic Targums, any place where God was appearing directly or God was doing something
directly or God was talked about in some physical sense or is having body parts, it would
add their word Memorah. So it was like the word of the Lord instead of just the Lord.
Yeah.
Well, the Samaritan Pettitoo kind of does that too. Except the way it does it is anytime
There's this physical sense or God appearing directly.
It says angel of God.
It's.
instead of just God.
Yeah.
So it adds angel to the front, basically.
But it's a similar kind of thing.
And so that falls into that whole second power in heaven idea.
The Samaritan's kind of had that going as well.
Right? This is evidence of that.
So that text again is then at the core because, of course,
In terms of what they're doing at the temple, they're following this
sacrificial regulations of their version of the Torah.
These are the commandments that are shaping Samaritan life, at least are supposed to be, right?
We have no reason to suspect they were more obedient to their Torah than the Jewish people were to the Torah as they were using it, but in theory.
And so as we go forward in time, as we mentioned, very fertile land under the cell, you could Greeks.
other
feeding the whole region with food grown there.
But during that period,
some of the same tensions start to arise in Samaria
that were arising in Judea.
In Judea, that ended up bringing about the Maca-Bian revolt.
Right, so, but in Samaria,
it doesn't quite get there for reasons
we'll talk about in a second.
In Samaria though, there are Samaritans,
members of the Samaritan people
who are attracted
to Greek culture and Greek learning and Greek and so sort of want to become Greeks.
And so they start hellenizing. They start adopting Greek practices, worshipping the Greek
gods, right? This kind of thing. And that of course creates attention with the Samaritan
people, the Samaritan high priest, right? Their existence, their wanting to retain their
identity as a people in their way of life and their religious identity. And there is this
Greek
imperial cultural force, right?
That is impeding on that.
But before that can reach a crisis point in Samaria,
it reaches a crisis point in Judea.
We talked before we have the episode not that long ago about the Hasmonians.
The Maccabeean revolt happens against the cell you could Greeks.
And they managed to establish an independent Judea for a time under a series of
Levi Kings which you
not supposed to have, but anyway, we talked about that there. And once they become independent,
they start to impinge upon Samaria. They also become expansionist. And there comes to be
this idea among the hams, has some sort of a reconquista that we're going to take back all
of the lands that were promised to all of the tribes. And those Samaritans don't have a legitimate
claim to them.
uh, draw any parallels you'd like. Um, and that culminates in, as we mentioned in the
Hezmonean episode, uh, John here canis around 150 BC, who is both the king and the high priest
at the same time. Yeah. In Judea, not good. And is in battle killing people. And is the
I've raised, but he goes and conquers Samaritan.
destroy the city of Samaria and destroy the temple of Mount Gharism.
Yeah and we should say the ruins of that temple are still there to this very
very day to this day. So it never gets rebuilt. That's right.
So this of course, right, we already saw, you know, the record in Ezra.
of the letter writing to the Persian Emperor that caused some of the
higher of the Jewish people against the Samaritan people.
After John here can, as you can see why the Samarians would have a grievance against the Jewish people.
They're destroyed temple in particular.
And so you have a fundamentally, this is a relationship that...
that from this point on is destined to never be good.
That's both of them self-identify as the true Israel of God
to the exclusion of the other.
The Judeans view the Samaritans as at best mixed.
They're sort of at best mixed race.
of them even in the first century like Josephus and stuff.
deny that there's a drop of Israelite blood in any of them, even though we know.
Yeah, big fact. That's not true. Because they take, you know, completely literally those hyperbolic
passages that we read earlier. Right. Right. And use those as proof. And so the idea that they have
any claim whatsoever. Right. To anything is completely rejected. Right. By by the Judeans throughout
the whole period.
Rome doesn't help the matter because so Rome comes in it's actually Pompey
during his tension before his war with Julius Caesar who comes in and annexes
both Samaria and Judea. Is this when he went into the temple in Jerusalem?
Yes. And was like wow there's nothing in the Holy of Holies. Yes. Yeah.
Yeah.
And so, but then in AD6, the Romans decide that there's no good reason from their perspective,
because again, they don't care about the people.
They just care about the land and its produce.
There's no good reason to have Judea and Samaria be separate provinces anymore.
And so they just merge them.
So, Samaria becomes part of Judea in terms of the Roman...
and civil government.
And as you might imagine,
that doesn't help because the Samaritans
and the Jewish people still hate each other.
So they also, the Romans also rebuilt the city of Samaria,
the city Samaria that John here can't say destroyed.
And that city gets renamed Sebastian.
Right. These subast. Yes. So all of you folks when you see subast or subastia referred to
in early church history, that's where they're talking about. That is the city of
Samaria. But even though they merged the provinces, neither Jews, nor Romans consider the Samaritans
to actually be Jews.
Yeah. Well, it also should be just to remember that that Jew is a subset of Israelite anyway.
You know, they're not simply due to it as a subset of Israelite. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
But the importance for that is that even now though now the Samaritans are living in the province of
Judea and therefore technically also Judeans, the Roman laws of tolerance and stuff that
that applied to the Judeans do not apply to the Samarins.
This is one of the reasons why the Romans didn't let them rebuild their temple.
And so once the Samaritan lands become part of Judea, again, draw any connections you'd
like the actual Judeans, right, the Jewish people, begin an aggressive series of settlements.
moving in to traditionally Samaritan territory, establishing Jewish villages to gradually
take territory away from the Samaritan's.
But that doesn't have a chance to get very far because in 8070, well, actually in starting
in 64, but the Jewish revolt happens.
Yeah.
and the Romans show up to take care of this in 8070.
And now the Samaritans not being Jews
as far as the Romans are concerned,
works to the Samaritans favor.
Yeah, because they're not gonna get put down
as the Romanaries, whatever.
Don't have any problem with the Samaritans right now.
Their problem is with the Jewish people
who have started this revolt.
And so the
the settlements as they move through Samaria,
the region on their way into Judea proper,
the Romans just depopulate those settlements.
And by that I mean kill everyone, right?
They go through and they wipe out about 50%
of the Jewish population.
in regions where Samaritans lived in 8070.
And then when the Barcochvera bolt happens 50 years later,
the Romans kill every single Jewish person they find.
So literally, it goes to zero.
That's not hyperbole.
The Romans, at the time of the Barcochvera rebellion,
It's literally massacre.
because the Romans had it at that point. I mean they had been repressive and brutal in 8070.
And so when they find out that didn't work, there's another uprising, they just, they literally
go scorched Earth, right? And so that's when the Jewish people who don't live in or who escape from
the Romans coming through Judea.
are banned from Judea. Can't return the name of the province has changed to Palestinian.
Yeah. And the city of Jerusalem, you know, you know, you definitely, you know, it becomes
a leacapalina. Yeah. Yeah. So yeah. So, but the Samarins are untouched. Yeah. I mean, incidentally,
I'm sure but I mean, in general, right, they have no beef with the Samarins. The Romans
have no beef with-
them and leave them largely alone. Right. So in the wake of all of these things, right,
for the Samaritan people and the wake of the destruction of their temple really,
right? And following that and then through the Roman period and therefore through the New Testament
the real center of their lives.
once again, it's not Sebastian, right? That was rebuilt by the Romans, but that's the center of Roman government, right?
Is the area around what comes to be called Nablus, and Nablus is really a corruption of the name Neopolis.
Yeah, Nablus.
Because it's ultimately it's from Arabic and Arabic does not have a peace out.
So, you know, yeah, so Nablus, Nablus.
Yes, and
Neopolis is of course most famous for having even segments of chocolate vanilla and strawberry ice cream.
Yes.
But that region around, obviously, Neopolis is a Greek city with a Greek name that means New City.
So to see built by the Greeks, I mean, the Greeks named a lot of stuff with that name like Naples in yeah.
in Italy. Yeah, he's not
going to build a new city.
It's the new city.
Not. Yes.
Napoli is Neopolis.
Nablus, which I mean, so this
is where you could go there.
That's the name of the town
now. Um, you know, so Jacob's
well still there. Yeah.
So now this is there.
That's where Jacob's well is.
But that's also the region
where Mount Garesum is Mount
Ebal, Shackum. Right.
So that is the
Remereton Harland.
Always the center of their
religious life, even though
they haven't been allowed to rebuild.
the temple on Mount Garesum. It's still a religious center, even though they don't have the temple.
And this is, you know, major figure. Obviously, the obvious figure at Church History is St.
Fautini. We'll talk about her a little more in the third half, who's living in this region.
Right? And who Christ encounters here. It's St. John's Gospel. But St. Justin Martyr
is later.
it writes from this region. So this is a significant place, right, for this area for some time to come.
So then in later history, and this is now much later, right. So it's like, well, what happens to
those Samaritan? Because the Samaritan stay living there, right? So eventually they do revolt against
Instagram.
But it's not until the 6th century AD.
So it's Christian Rome now by this point.
Yes. It is what is commonly called the Byzantine Empire at this point.
And there are two revolts, one in five, twenty-five, and one in five fifty-five,
both of which are cracked down upon by Saint Justinian
when he was the emperor.
And shall we say, especially the second cracked down in five fifty-five,
populated the region quite a bit.
Yeah. And St. Justinian, unlike the Assyrians, right, or some of these other rulers, empires
did not himself resettle and repopulate the area. The troops withdrew just sort of leaving
this void, right, within the population. But this is still
very fertile farmland. This is still good land and everything. And so what happened was,
in the middle of this century, a number of nomadic Arab tribes moved into the region and
settled there of their own accord. And so it was sort of repopulated by these nomads
who put down roots now that they had this land available. They're sort of like frontier
settlers in the United States, right? They went just went...
in there and just sort of stake to claim, built homes, put down roots, right, and started working
the land, gave up nobanism. But it's not that long after this that the Muslim conquest began.
And so there was not enough time before the Muslim conquest for any of these new settlers.
to sort of be inculturated and come to think of themselves as Samaritans.
Yeah. Right? So you have the Samaritans who are left after the Second Revolt still living there,
still identifying as Samaritans, still practicing Samaritan religion. But these other people who come
and settle don't really get integrated before the Muslim conquest. And so when Islamic armies conquer
conquer some area.
These groups don't have any particular allegiance to Samaritan religion. They have whatever tribal religion they had as nomads.
And so there's just this huge mass conversion to Islam.
Yeah.
So those new settlers pretty much all convert to Islam.
And a lot of the actual Samaritans up to that point also along the way through history end up converting to Islam.
Right.
And hey, I mean, honestly, there's not a huge radical difference at this point.
Yeah, I mean, Islam at that period.
Yeah.
In the seventh-day century, there's not a huge difference between Islam and Samaritanism, religiously.
Yeah, right.
Obviously Christianity, big differences, right.
Right.
smaller differences with Judaism, but with with Samaritanism
They don't have a temple.
And stuff.
It's not a huge pull, right?
When the Muslims show up and are claiming the God-day worship is the God of Abraham, I mean,
that's not a huge lift for a Samarit, right?
So there's not a huge barrier to conversion.
And so there's a lot of conversion.
And so by the time you get to today, to 2026, there's estimated to be less than 1,000
and Samaritan.
Yes.
Yeah, there's about nine, yeah, around 900.
And I looked at, so where do they live?
Like, so the largest group is there,
still in that same place, which is amazing.
And then there's also an almost as big group near Tel Aviv.
And so I was really interested in this.
So I went and looked up, I was like,
OK, what is the modern shape of Samaritan religion?
is 9
100 plus people. So there's some interesting differences with Judaism that people might find
fascinating. So number one, they regard Moses as being the final prophet. Right. So that's
a big difference right there, right? Like all these other prophets that that Judah has,
you know, recognizes that we would all think of as Judaism and I'm certainly part of Christianity.
I don't have that. It's just Moses is a lot.
last one. And then as we hinted at earlier, they regard the break as having happened with
Eli, the priest, right? That Eli was this kind of rebel figure. And they say that he offered
illicit sacrifices that he made his own copy of the Ark of the Covenant. So he made like
like, you know that dog.
the arc that, oh, that, you know, that the Judeans always regard it as the arc, they say that he
he copied that. So that's just a copy that they had the real arc and that he made a copy of the
the Mount Gares and Temple. So again, you can see it's sort of this idea, but they're the breakway
religion, right? Well, also, I mean, Eli, not a good guy. Right, right. So not entirely implausible.
Yeah, right so yeah
Yeah, and so in first Samuel the solution to Eli is sort of Samuel
the prophet, but if you don't accept any prophets after Moses, yeah. Right. Yep.
So they do continue to maintain a priesthood. So this is interesting because that's different
from rabbinic Judaism which does not have a priesthood. Right, they have rabbis which just means
teachers, they don't have a priesthood.
And the priest...
is traditionally they don't have, they don't hold down jobs.
So it's sort of like this Levitical idea, right?
That you don't, they don't work except doing the priestly stuff.
But there's a kind of practical problem amongst the modern Samaritans,
which is that about 28% of the total population that people is part of this priestly family.
So you can't have 72% of the population supporting 28% who do
only this kind of stuff, right?
If you have 900 people, it's hard.
So as a result, a lot of them do have jobs,
just for purely practical reasons.
There is a high priest, so there's multiple priests,
but there's a high priest.
And the high priest is whoever's the oldest male member
of that family.
So it's not father, the son.
So like for instance, the current high priest,
the sort of heir apparent, I think,
is a younger brother of his.
So if he dies, then that younger brother
will become the next surgery.
It will not necessarily go to one of the sons of the high priest.
They do still offer sacrifice, but the only sacrifice they offer is Passover.
So all the other living sacrifices, even though that's in their version of the Torah, they're not doing those things.
That's because of the temple.
Yeah.
What's interesting is they will go to the ruins of that temple on Mount Gherizm.
And they will do the pass over there.
There's like, there's photos.
You can see photos of...
of of of of of lamb.
You know, lambs lined up to bread to be roasted and stuff.
So so they're they're doing that. It's very interesting.
How do they understand the why there's only a few of them?
Like they regarded as actually a confirmation of a prophecy
that that they're supposed to be this twin length that occurs
before the end of the whole remnant.
Exactly. Exactly. It's exactly that idea.
So then then the final thing that I want to
mention about this before we take our second break is so the end of the world.
Okay, so they have an eschatology, right?
There's an end of the world that's going to come.
And at this point, then there's this figure called the, and I have no idea how to pronounce
this, but I'm going to say what I think it is the Taheb T-A-H-E-B is weak.
It's anglicized.
The Taheb will emerge.
So this guy is another prophet, but he's like, he's a Messiah.
Moses, he's going to be a prophet for 40 years. He's going to restore the kingdom of Israel. So then
the faithful remnant will become the basis for the restoration. The dead are all going to be raised.
To have means the restorer by the way. Oh really? Okay. Okay.
The restorer cares for the restorer. Yeah. Yeah.
And you'd expect that because because Messiah is the king, right? The annoyed to the one.
They have no connection to the divinic king.
Yeah, right.
Exactly.
exactly. He's going to discover the Tabernacle, which is hidden all this time, and he's going
to bring it to Mount Gharism. And then when his mission is complete, he's going to die and
be buried next to Joseph, right? So the father truly, almost like a second Abraham in some
ways, right, to the Samaritans. So he's going to be buried next to Joseph. And that's going
to be the restoration, the completion of everything. So it's really interesting. And
We talked about of course the Samaritan Pentatuc Samaritan Torah earlier. That's on the internet. You can sit there and read it
And of course there's translations you can read of it on the internet
So if you're interested in going and looking at that and just seeing what that's like you can you can go have a look
So all this is spot and make a complete list of all 6000 variants
Exactly
A lot of them probably would not be noticeable to someone who reads only English because
Like you know he perspelt and
And that's how good the translation is.
Yeah, translation makes a point.
following the word order and stuff. Yeah, exactly. Exactly. So, so yeah, this is still a group that exists.
There's not a lot of them, but they're there still holding on after all these years and they have
some interesting distinctives from from rabbinic Judaism. Probably the most notable one to my mind
is that they continue to have a priesthood. When they say they are descended from Aaron. So yeah,
Yep, yep. So that kind of brings us up to the present time. So then
What we're going to discuss in the third half is, does this mean anything for Christians?
Where are we going with all this?
So we're going to take our second break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Blinded by rage.
We live in a world that commonly sees the passion of anger as a virtue that can be used
to help write wrongs.
But what do scripture and the fathers say about anger is expressing outrage at societal
ills a true reflection of God's attitude towards these evils, or does it instead blindest
his presence?
Father, theater, pochini and Oswin Craton joined together to examine how anger affects
our journey towards theosis.
it today at store.in
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
We're talking about the Samaritans and in the first half we...
covered what the Bible says about the formation of that people and then the second
half we kind of talked about them as a people as they developed over history and
finished up talking about their current existence, their beliefs or practices
of those 900 people. I mean it's amazing. It's amazing that they're still around.
But so yeah, so all right so where are we father? Should we go back to Genesis?
What do you think?
I have to relay some tragic news.
Uh-oh.
They closed the local CCs pizza.
I'm...
Do we need a moment of silence?
I will soldier on through the rest of this episode.
But if I seam off, people.
It's probably good you're not on camera at this time.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Um...
Yeah, unfortunately that break was long enough
long enough to mostly pull myself together.
Yeah. No calls. Well, we have one that's really off topic. I mean, do you want to take
it? This person is still hanging on Mike hasn't hung up on them yet. Let's do it. Okay,
let's do it. All right. So just belay what I said to you in our private chat, Mike. Let's
take Nikolai from Texas. I see your passing notes in class. I know absolute. Oh, all the
time. Welcome to Laura Spier's podcast, Nikolai.
Oh, you're falling for my trap, fathers.
No, thank you.
Take my call, fathers.
Damn, that Paul guy won't leave you alone.
I can give him to knock it off if you want.
He's my god, brother.
So just let me know.
So is there a connexion conspiracy, boy, God?
I saw a solid nougie.
He goes the same, he goes the same, same churches I do.
Wow.
Yeah, what's up, Texas?
on behalf of Texas Hello.
But yeah, so this is kind of relating to the previous topic.
So I'm sorry, I tried to get in,
but I couldn't quite make it out of the wire.
So I was listening to, you know,
this always comes up with our, you know,
dear Protestant family members,
the question of icons
and one thing that comes up in the debates, of course,
and in Father's, in Father's Human Debate with Gavin,
Um, are you in a first name basis with Dr. Orland?
You just call him Gavin.
I mean, I mean, we all know who we, we all know it.
I mean, Dr. Orland.
I'm just messing with you because it's fun.
I appreciate that.
Um, I'll take his compliment.
Um, but yeah, so usually comes up either Saint Bernice or Saint
Bronca.
Anyway, so he has a passage.
Um, well, the two things they coded are the anionic.
letter to Constantina, where he appears to criticize her for requesting icons, I think either
of Jesus and possibly of Peter and Paul. But then in his history of the church, he talks
about, he brings up a statue from the region where he was from.
I suppose the commission.
by St. Bernice or St. Veronica, the woman with the issue of blood of her touching juices
robe, and then there's like a plant that grow by that that has maracas medicinal qualities,
and some people have come and been at the statue and take cutting for the plant.
Kind of like the man at St. John's tomb, kind of a deal.
And so, but Father Stephen was saying that he does not think that that account is authentic,
kind of just
is why if I may dare to pull so far off the tracks.
All right. That's all you father. Well, so there's there's no evidence of it outside of UCBS
at all. Right. Like no local records at all. No other fathers mentioning it. No remains of it.
no record of it being destroyed. Right?
like the stuff at St. John's grave, you could still go there, right? Like Jacob's well,
you could go there. It's in the sort of the basement of a church now, right? Like these
kind of sites, we pretty much know where they are. They're still there. Or we know when
they were destroyed. Right? We have, we have some kind of record. And there's just nothing
about this, except this one mentioned in UCBS, and UCBS is super unreliable.
You see, there's a lot of clearly agendas stuff where he shapes things based on his own personal opinions and beliefs.
Like, he literally invents people, like John the Presbyter, to try to argue against the acceptance of the book of Revelation as canonical.
right. He invents a historical
personage. There's a lot of
stuff like that in UCBS. So I in
general don't hang my hat on
anything that you can own and
he's also a heretic. There's
the reason he's not Saint UCBS.
He's an Aryan. People say
semi-Aryan but I think I've got
the goods on him because I've
actually read his uh...
his elaboration of the gospel, not just his church history, and I think he's a full-on
Aryan who just guy who deliberately tried to get sneak around NIC01 as a semi-Aryan.
But anyway, he's a heretic.
So, yeah, anything that isn't corroborated by someone other than Eusebius, I am dubius.
Just in general.
And rhetorically, like if I'm debating a Protestant,
and they are trying to hang their hat on something that's only attested to by UCBS,
I might be want to point to something in UCBS that I know they're not going to want to believe is true
true to use as a counter-argument.
Well, there you go.
First back on a couple on a couple
fronts.
One, of course, you know, with
historical accounts, we're always
asking, like, you know, do they have
any reason to lie?
Yeah.
And so I would think it would be
the opposite of that because if the
layered contentina is correct, is
authentic, then it seems strange
that you would bring up something
something that seems to...
supports icon veneration on the other end.
And then the other thing that I would,
the other one I pushed back on was there's a,
again, I'm not, I haven't read the original sources,
but apparently there's this guy named Sosa Manos
who was actively coming the mid fifth century, I believe.
And he says that Julian the apostates
Destroy the staff.
you? Yeah, so ... so so so zamen
cribbed things from UCBS, so I mean we
don't have any we have lots of records of
things Julie and the apostate did
while he was alive, not from
centuries later that don't mention
that, I would be prone to think that
that could very
very well be. Right. See, I have nothing hanging on this. Like if we dig up the statute
tomorrow, I'll be like, cool. That'll be really helpful in argumentation. But I'm thinking
about this in terms of like is pointing to this at all useful to me. Right. Like do you
think if I brought that up as an example to Gavin Orland to prove iconography was apostolic?
Do you think he'd he'd he'd accept it?
I have my doubts.
So that's, you know, like I mean, I would be totally fine with it being true.
I'm just saying there's plenty of reason to doubt it, such that I wouldn't hang my hat on it.
That's why I use that language of hanging my hat on it.
Gotcha.
Do you know anything about the
I'm not sure if I can say that right.
Fellows do Regius.
I don't know if you know
anything about that.
Yeah, I don't know
anything about that one.
I know.
I know so it's been.
Is an apologist in places
for you, CBS, right?
So someone could argue.
Right.
Like I tried to use that could
use that say, oh, well.
He's trying to support you.
CBS has claimed that it was
there by someone of Jackson
says, well, where is it?
I went there and it's not
there.
Oh, I don't know.
I went there and it's not there.
Well, Julia, the apostate destroyed it. Right. So, you know, it may be true that it was there.
Julia, the apostate destroyed it. It's just I don't have anything to really hang my hat on that
in terms of proof. I mean, for me, when I was, you know, doing research before my conversion,
I did find it helpful. But I mean, you know, it depends on like, you know, you have to be,
it depends on the disposition of the person, how like willing they are to,
of to actually like, recon.
their position, I guess, that probably depends on what.
That probably influences the amount of weight
they're going to give stuff.
I mean, I think in terms of using it to argue against the letter,
right, in terms of saying like, hey, are you saying this is the same guy?
This doesn't seem to match.
I mean, I think that's a valid usage of it.
Because regardless of whether it's true or not,
UCB has did write that.
Yeah, I was thinking of someone else.
I was thinking of someone else saying, oh, the letter is fake.
Yeah, so I was just so.
Right, it's easy.
that. But that could be helpful if the person you're arguing with is
hinging their case on the letter being real. Now you've gotten them to admit
the letters fake, right?
Yeah, that's good. So.
Okay. Well, thank you for sharing your take, Father. I appreciate that for you
to the time of the park from that. And next time for Father Andrew,
I'm not going to bother you guys any longer. I'll let you guys finish up.
But next time for Father Andrew, I do have a question about Christian
Kitch.
So I'll be saying that one for later.
You should have led with that one.
Well anyway, yeah, well, I hadn't quite collected my thoughts for that one.
That's okay.
The saints, the little saints plushies I'm seeing in some of the church stores.
I don't see that in Eastern Europe when I was growing up over there.
So I don't.
So we'll get to that later, maybe.
Unless you want to answer it now, it's up to you.
I mean, I am not in favor of saints plus Jesus if that's what you're at.
Yeah, same. Okay, they came up to me when I saw a guy was like making was doing some kind of
star for like playing cards, but with icons on them, which yeah, I mean, like, I'm not against
the idea. Like if people are making toys for kids, like actual like toys for kids, I that wouldn't
bug me. But like to make them collectibles or something like that? No, no, no, well, well,
I would push back on that father
because you know that kids are
not natural, responsible with their toys.
And so, I'm thinking of like the
resurrection play set complete with
Jesus action figure that me and my brothers
received on Easter one year in the 90s.
I don't know anything about that in particular,
but that's different than that's
different.
Like, for instance, I've seen,
for small kids.
I've seen, I saw a saint Moses the Ethiopian doll.
And it's actually was a brilliantly done.
So like you kind of flip the skirt of the tunic up
and here you have him as the robber
and then you flip it the other way
and he sort of, now he's a saint.
He's depicted as older and looks like a monk.
And so it kind of represents his conversion.
And yeah, it just really kind of depends
on the nature of the thing.
And so yeah.
Yeah, yeah, you're just like your Jesus action figure gets gets left laying around it
just doesn't seem very respectful.
I don't I wouldn't be in favor of a Jesus action figure.
I mean, an action figure is right.
Like what are action figures that's that's not the same thing as like like what I just described.
You know, so it just would really kind of depend.
Yeah.
There's a whole world.
I'm like, I'm not personally super engaged with these things, but some of them have come
into my house because my wife...
knows way more about children's toys than I have ever in my entire life even considered.
But then also like working for a publisher, there are some toys and some of these kinds
of things that come through our store.
And people who know way more about these things have selected some really, I think some good
stuff actually.
But there is a way to kind of commodify, you know, commoditize or whatever.
that I think is not okay, you know?
It just feels like, yeah, the American evangelical culture,
I mean, you know, just flowing with the way of the Convert's kind of flowing into
the, we're having like an interesting melding of like, you know,
it's this whole thing of like the, the, the, the gradual immersive American Orthodoxy
and trying to find there.
And we're like, yeah, we're working out what our American Orthodox culture is
and there's come some missteps.
I mean the thing is like you may not be aware
instance if you're from, I don't know where you're from originally, but, uh, but like, for instance,
there is, there is this figure in Greece called, uh, Kiria Saracosti. So basically, Mrs. Lent,
right? And Kiria Saracosti is a doll with seven feet and you tear off one of the feet
during each week of Lent to mark. So it's a kind of like Lent calendar of sorts,
like an advent calendar kind of thing, but it's for lent.
And it's a doll that is, you know, it's like a paper doll.
That is, that is increased.
So I mean, it is a thing in some traditional, this kind of stuff is a thing in some traditional
Orthodox countries.
It's not a doll of a specific saint or, you know, holy person.
It's just like this random figure with seven legs, right?
As far as I know, yes.
But like I said, I think it's okay to let these things work themselves out.
And just to watch.
as it sort of sifts, you know, and think about, okay, what is this actually accomplishing?
Is this respectful? The truth is, is that, you know, I have four children, three of whom are boys.
And while there's never been a Jesus action figure lying around in my house, I will not say that every
single icon in my house has always been treated completely respectfully at every single moment. Does
that mean I should keep icons out of the hands of my children? Because they're not going to treat
them perfectly? No, it just means I have to teach them.
you know, about icons.
But the icon is designed with a certain, you know,
of course.
Of course, if I may abuse,
if I may abuse,
of course, returns, yes.
Of course.
Like, you know, action figure, yeah.
So yeah.
I think the key is just to, you know,
to try to be sensitive to what's appropriate
and rather than making categorical pronouncements,
especially because I like,
I'm the kind of person that likes to make...
categorical pronouncements based on my taste. And my taste is not necessarily the overriding
thing. Like there are children's books that I think are ridiculous, but are actually
are great. But it strikes me as ridiculous. There's nothing blasphemous about it, nothing
theoretical about it. So yeah, I think it's like I said, we just have to be sensitive about
these things and you know, allow some room for mistakes. It's okay.
Okay, it's okay.
These things shift out.
What's that?
Doesn't someone have to say it's a mistake, though?
Yeah, maybe.
Absolutely.
But give some space.
Let creative people do what they're gonna do.
And allow the process of the church's culture forming
to sift through these things.
It will.
It's gonna be okay.
I'm sure it will be. It's just my personal preferences get annoyed in the meantime, but I mean the truth is is that even traditional, even traditional Orthodox cultures are not perfect at this.
You know,
like yeah, maybe but but how like go to any traditional Orthodox culture in the Mediterranean and you will find easy access to evil eye.
You know, amulets.
For thousands of years, they've had these.
around so they still need to work on that.
Clearly. You know, so yeah, yeah.
Somehow we manage.
It's okay.
So anyway, all right.
Well, thanks for your call.
What was that question?
Will there be an Orthodox Holy Land experience?
Bark.
Yes, probably a recreation of Constant Noble.
There we go.
Yes.
people would be into that.
Anyway, all right.
I want to ride the beast that goes in the boss race, right?
Those should be a whole lot of the beast of the boss
versus.
All right.
Thanks for calling to come.
Okay.
We're going to take one more call and we have Caleb calling
from Kenosha, Wisconsin.
Welcome to Lord Spears podcast.
Caleb is this better be good Caleb.
We're two hours past his bedtime.
That's right.
I was going to say it's an extra late night tonight.
And I still have an hour and I have to drive an hour home after
this.
Just put that out there, believe it.
you father and your
I'm like tinkerbell you know you have to believe in me so I could continue to exist
I'm throwing on my hand getting almost beaten in the
I'm an agra gourd anyway what's on your mind um I um was just talking with some friends
a couple days ago about yom kippur the modern you know process that the Jewish the Jewish people do
And I don't know if this is a weird translation into English or if this is...
certain rabbinic circles, but the prayer that's prayed when the people are
swinging the chicken on the bone there had an English that's translated and
unmovable sources saying this is my exchange, this is my substitute, this is my
expiation, the rooster shall go to death and I shall proceed to a good law and
life in peace. And to me that sounds a lot like
substitutionary language. I know most useful in recent orthodox
that I've heard talk don't let-
like Penal's looks to do share at home and but it sounds an awful lot like.
You know that someone during am I missing something?
Did they go wrong at some point?
Is this always kind of been the view of this or modern kind of way of the view of Michigan?
So I ask you father Steven, is there poultry substitutionary at tone
going on here?
Well, so that's what the P really stands for as we all know.
Obviously this is not a remotely biblical ritual.
Right.
This is discussed nowhere in the Hebrew Scriptures, right?
So this is a practice that developed later.
And so it's based on understandings that developed later.
But
and honestly, you this is something I should probably ask by Orthodox Jewish
friend about right because this is such a late development or a panic
We're a bit ag-
is them that like I haven't studied that far forward into the future. But even if, shall
we say we take a completely literal reading and that is some kind of substitution, in that
case it would be the substitution of the chicken for a person which seems weird. And it's
It's also technically not a sacrifice.
It's not a sacrificial ritual or they wouldn't be allowed to do it.
So it's weird on a number of levels, right?
It's weird in the fact that it can't technically be a sacrifice.
So even with that modern rabbinic practice, it wouldn't be sacrifice this penal substitution.
It would be some kind of penal substitutionary ritual that's not a sacrifice.
And also that there...
the big objection of Orthodox Judaism to the idea of penal substitutionateonement,
their objection is the idea that a righteous man would suffer for the sins
of a wicked person. Right, that God would punish an innocent human. Right. So I don't know that
they'd have the same qualms about God punishing an innocent chicken. Um,
Um, the seems related to pardoning a turkey at Thanksgiving.
Like, uh,
I mean, it's honestly that Turkey committed that he must be part of.
Yes, honestly, I think I'd have to ask a modern, rabbinic Jewish person to explain this,
but to me, it smells like a good luck ritual killing a chicken.
Yeah.
Like, it smells like a little bit like folk magic.
it smells like a kind of super
delicious good luck thing. I was talking about with some friends and related, it's definitely
not a sacrifice. And I've never heard any, any serious reformed Christian ever trying
to use this as an argument as the right to like no one. No. Yeah. Well, yeah, because
it's so post biblical. Right. Like, I mean, best case scenario, you prove that like modern
Rubinic Jews believe in some kind of penal substitution but that
they believe in a lot of things that Christians don't believe in. Advice
versa, right? So that doesn't get you much. Yep. Exactly. Exactly. All right.
Well, thanks for calling Caleb. All right. You two have a good night. You two. All right.
Okay. It's got a bright affsick enough man.
That's these rickets.
All right.
Yeah.
Uh, yeah.
Third half.
Half.
You got some toothpicks you could put in your eyelids there to keep keep going here. I might just I might just I might just drive home and you could just you know.
I'll just finish it out talk off into the sunset.
I'm going to be I'm going to be out by owner cognizant said though I'm going to be.
I can't I can't say.
I'm like cut him off cut him off.
Okay.
All right.
Back to Genesis.
What's going on?
Yeah, we're going back to the next one.
Next we promised we're looping back to the historical Ephraim.
to Joseph Sun Ephraim.
And this is kind of review, right?
But because we have talked about this on the show before.
But basically what we want to talk about now here
is we draw the episode to a close eventually three hours
from now is what is the theological significance of this?
So we talked about the history of the Samaritans,
like the Old Testament era history,
A little bit of the new...
test in the background of the Samaritans. Lots of cool tidbits that'll
color your reading of different parts of the Bible hopefully give you some
added depth we even gave you some fun facts about the Samaritans today and
stuff but at the core of it what is there any real theological significance to
this? The answer is yes. Yeah, yeah, actually. And here we and so to get it that we
have to start with the role E-frem plays, right?
in the biblical text and to get there we're going to start with the actual original Ephraim, right?
The Ephraim, the son of Joseph the patriarch.
And so the first really important place to go is Genesis.
So Genesis 48, we've talked about several times.
48 and 49 are sort of the testament of Jacob.
chapter 49, Jacob is blessing his 12.
sons and it's sort of the blessings are sort of prophetic about what's going to happen with the different tribes.
We've talked about that. Chapter 48, he blesses Joseph's two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim. And so there's
a couple sections of that that we want to revisit here. So first one is Genesis chapter 48 verse 5.
Okay. Which says, and now your two sons who are born to you in the land of Egypt before I came to
Egypt are mine. Ephraim and Manasseh shall be mine as Rubin
and Simeon are. Right. So this is the speaker here is Jacob. Right. Yeah. And so he says,
you're and the you is Joseph. Right. So you're two sons. Joseph's two sons. He's saying,
are now mine. Meaning this is adoption language, meaning Manasseh and Ephraim were not
be reckoned as his grandchildren through Joseph but as his sons.
Right, if we may as a sons and not just his sons.
Right, in terms of the tribes, right.
But as Rubin and Simeon are who were his first born sons.
Yeah.
So in Genesis 48 verse five, this is part of what I was talking about way back in the long ago time when this episode started.
About when you get to the end of Genesis.
This verse is basically saying that Jacob considers Ephraim his first.
So what would you expect coming out of this?
So, Ephraim unbelievably prominent here.
And then in verses 14 through 20,
we get to the actual blessing that Jacob gives to Ephraim in particular.
which says,
that is right hand and laid it on the hand of Ephraim who was the younger. And his left hand on
the head of Manasseh crossing his hands for Manasseh was the first born. And he blessed Joseph and said,
the God before whom my father's Abraham and Isaac walked, the God who has been my shepherd all
my life long to this day, the angel who has redeemed me from all evil blessed the boys. And in them let my
name be carried on and the name of my father's Abraham and Isaac and let them grow into a multitude
in the midst of the Earth.
That's positive.
there a second. So just a couple of things to notice in the blessing. First of all,
Manasa is actually the older son, but Ephraim gets to the right hand. Blessing. There's going to be
more of that here in a second, right? But again, if we're just tracking through Genesis,
right? Abraham has Ishmael and Isaac Isaac becomes the firstborn. Isaac has Esau and Jacob
Jacob becomes the first born.
Jacob has the 12 sons.
Joseph is the first born of his preferred wife.
He sort of becomes the one the story follows.
And now Joseph has two sons.
Minas and Ephraim, it looks like,
oh, Ephraim is becoming the first born.
Right? If we're just tracking through Genesis
of the patterns.
The other thing worth noting is,
and this is, remember our Old Testament Christology.
Remember.
Some of those theophonies were like the angel of the Lord who wrestled with Jacob.
Notice he identifies the God of Abraham and Isaac, the God who is his shepherd, and the angel
who he wrestled with, he's identified as the same person. Yeah, interesting.
Or not the same person but the same being, right? Yeah.
Okay, so continue.
Okay, continue on with verse 17.
When Joseph saw
that his father laid his right hand on the head of Ephraim, it displeased him, and he took
his father's hand to move it from Ephraim's head to Manasse's head. Joseph said to his father,
not this way my father, since this one is the first born, put your right hand on his head.
But his father refused and said, I know my son, I know, he also shall become a people,
and he also shall be great. Nevertheless, his younger brother should be greater than he,
and his offspring shall become the fullness of the Gentiles.
So he blessed them that day saying,
by you Israel will pronounce blessings saying,
God make you as Ephraim and as Manasseh.
Thus he put Ephraim before Manasseh.
Okay.
So now a couple of things here.
Not only does he give this blessing,
he gives this blessing to Joseph Suns
before he blesses his own Suns.
Yeah. After adopting them,
gives Ephraim the younger one this special blessing.
So pronounced a blessing, right? He says that Israel by you, Israel will pronounce blessings. He's
Israel. Yeah, yeah. That's his name. Right. So he's saying by this, the people, all the descendants
will bless each other by saying, God make you as Ephraim and Manasseh.
So this is more like Ephraim you'd think this is the most important right
They're kind of it.
And then there's the detail of the prophecy, which is kind of cryptic here, as most of the
prophecies in chapter 49 are regarding the tribes, until you read the later history, they're
kind of cryptic, right?
Like why does it keep calling Benjamin a Viper?
Like what?
Benjamin's a kid.
You find out later, right?
So the stuff about Dan, you find out later.
Right.
So here his offspring will become the fullness.
the Gentiles. I know a number of you already know where this is going because we've talked about it
before and you recognize that phrase from St. Paul. We'll get there. Indeed. Right. But that phrase is
important. Okay. So Ephraim has this great destiny. It seems like right at Genesis. And as you
track the painting, they're the biggest tribe as we said, the most numerous take the land big
the numbers in the land, right?
They be...
become the basis of one of the two kingdoms, the larger of the two kingdoms, the more powerful
of the two kingdoms, all of this.
And so you might think, well, okay, but then the Assyrians wipe them out.
And so that's done, right?
Tons of potential kind of wasted, right?
Like most people thought about me when I was in college.
But that's not actually what we see when we read the text.
of the Bible after the destruction of the Northern Kingdom.
So what are some of the things that the prophets have to say
after the destruction of the Northern Kingdom of Israel
about Ephraim?
And first of all, what we're going to read is from Jeremiah 31.
This is in most Bibles.
This is not the chapter numbers are weird.
Yeah, because Jeremiah is the next study Bible.
But this is general Bible.
Is it like this differently?
Yeah.
Jeremiah 31
1 verses 15 through 20.
And Jeremiah 31, remember, this is the new covenant passage.
This is the chapter where God is talking about what's going to happen
when he renews the covenant with Israel.
All right, starting with verse 15.
Thus says the Lord,
a voice is heard in Rama,
lamentation in bitter weeping.
Rachel is weeping for her children.
She refuses to be comforted for her children
because they are no more.
Thus says the Lord,
Keep your-
voice from weeping and your eyes from tears for there is a reward for your work declares
the Lord and they shall come back from the land of the enemy.
There is hope for your future declares the Lord and your children shall come back to their
own country.
I have heard from grieving, you have disciplined me and I was disciplined like an untrained
calf bring me back that I may be restored for you are the Lord my God.
For after I had turned away I relented and after I was instructed I struck my thigh
I was ashamed that I was confounded because I-
the disgrace of my youth. Is Ephraim my dear son? Is he my darling child? For as often as I speak
against him, I do remember him still. Therefore my heart yearns for him, I will surely have mercy on him
to Claire's the Lord." Yeah, so everybody immediately recognized the first verse, I'm sure.
The fact of Collar referred to it earlier. The voice has heard in Rama, I mean, he's been reweeping,
Rachel weeping for her children.
Right?
How many of you have gone and read the next several verses?
Right.
So it talks about her drawing her tears, right?
But then it was say because there's hope for the future and her children,
who was Rachel's firstborn?
Joseph.
Yeah.
And then verse 18, I have heard
Ephraim grieving
This is Jeremiah writing this.
So this is at the time of the fall of the Southern Kingdom.
This is like 140 years later, after the structure of the Northern Kingdom.
And it's gone.
But how is it described?
As Ephraim speaks to God, there's this Convert dialogue here between Ephraim and God.
Ephraim doesn't say, I'm destroyed, I'm done. He's been disciplined. Like an untrained
calf, which is an amazing analogy when you think about Jeroboam's son of Nebath. Right?
describes the sin of the northern kingdom as the sin and shame.
name of his youth. That is Ephraim's childhood, that history. Since of his youth, and he
had to be disciplined. But God says what? God says he still loves him. He's dear to him.
He says, dear son, and he's going to have mercy on him, the end of the punishment. Meaning
that destiny for...
Ephraim that was prophesied back there in Genesis by Jacob, right, is still pending.
And God's going to bring it about, right? And so the story of Ephraim of the northern kingdom
of those 10 tribes does not end in 722 BC when the Assyrians take them out, right? That's the end of
the childhood that's the end of the
misspent youth. Now another passage, it talks about a room. This one's from Ezekiel chapter 37
verses 15 through 28. This is the passage that comes immediately after the dry bones.
Passage. Okay. The word of the Lord came to me. Son of man, take a stick and write on it for Judah,
and the people of Israel associated with him, then take another stick and write on it for Joe
the stick of Ephraim and all the house of Israel associated with them, and join them one to another
into one stick, that they may become one in your hand. And when your people say to you, will you not
tell us what you mean by these? Say to them, thus says the Lord God, behold, I'm about to take the
stick of Joseph that is in the hand of Ephraim, and the tribes of Israel associated with him, and I
will join with it the stick of Judah and make them one stick, that they may be one in my hand. When the
sticks on which you ride or in your hand.
before their eyes, and then say to them,
Thus says the Lord God, behold,
I will take the people of Israel from the nations among which they have gone,
and will gather them from all around and bring them to their own land,
and I will make them one nation in the land on the mountains of Israel,
and one king shall be king over them all, and they shall no longer be two nations,
and no longer divided into two kingdoms.
They shall not defile themselves any more with their idols and their detestable things,
or with any of their transgressions, but I will save them from all the back
writings in which they have sinned and will cleanse them and they shall be my people and
I will be their God.
My servant David shall be king over them and they shall all have one shepherd.
They shall walk in my rules and be careful to obey my statutes.
They shall dwell in the land that I gave to my servant Jacob where your fathers lived.
They and their children and their children's children shall dwell there forever and David
my servant shall be their prince forever.
I'll make a covenant a piece with them. It should be an everlasting covenant.
with them. And I will set them in their land and multiply them and we'll set my sanctuary
in their midst forevermore. My dwelling place will be with them and I will be their God and
they should be my people. Then the nations will know that I am the Lord who sanctifies Israel
when my sanctuary is in their midst forevermore. So there's lots of other stuff we could read too,
obviously. But again, Father Andrew is liable to lose consciousness at any moment.
It's already had.
So that's why I have to keep them reading just to keep them awake.
So, uh, right, but but here's another one, right?
So the promise is not, I'm going to bring the Judahites, the Judeans, the Jewish people, from all over the world, back and place my Messiah over them.
That's not the promise.
No.
The promise is explicitly
explicitly.
Judah, yes, right, is one stick, right? And Joseph, Ephraim, is the other stick,
which is also going to be brought back from the nations according to this prophecy,
and they're going to be united, and they're going to be united by the Messiah,
who is going to come and be king over both of them.
So there are these prophecies in the Hebrew Bible.
As we're coming right into the period of the New Testament.
Period of Christ's earthly ministry.
How did they think this was going to happen?
Right?
Because the, I mean the Judah part is
easy relatively right there are people who are practicing you days most who are you know
following the Torah who are part considered themselves part of the Jewish people. We're
following the no-most of the Jewish people the Torah right there in different parts of
the world okay we just get them all together and the Messiah comes and he's their king right
I mean not simple but I mean within the realm of possibility over the course of history surely
right? But the other part. Where are we going to get ephryamites?
Hmm, monassins, ruminights, gattites.
Attend lost tribes. Quote, quote, quote. Yeah. Where are we going to get them? How are they
How was the Messiah going to do that? Right?
Is it right literally in the resurrection that that happens? Right? It's only after everyone's
resurrected from the dead. Well, the Israelites will be resurrected from the dead too. Right? The
exile will rule over the resurrected people maybe. Now, we already saw a little bit in the history
of the Samaritans, how the Hasmoneans understood this, the Hasmoneans.
You know, especially like John here canis considered himself to probably be the Messiah, right? And so his motive that was Reconquista.
All of the land that used to belong to the 12 tribes now belongs to the Judahites, essentially.
Right? And again, make any connections that you'd like. Right? All of this land that was
promised to the 12 tries was promised to the Jewish people.
Now there is obviously there's the problem we already alluded to with the fact that those
promises were land promises were fulfilled at the end of Joshua, but also an even bigger
problem in terms of the Torah for this approach is that that land was never promised to Judah,
right, or Benjamin, and no land was promised to leave by.
Sorry, dispensation lists, right?
So if the land that was promised to Ephraim, unless you've got me some Ephraimites,
there's no biblical claim whatsoever in any point in history for Judahites, Jewish people,
to claim Ephraimite land.
Right? And not just at the tribal level, remember, go through...
numbers, the land alignments are granular. Such as at the tribal level, it's the tribe
and then the clan has certain lands within that. And then each family had particular land
within that. That land was promised to that individual family. Yeah, it was supposed
to revert to them every 50th year. So if that family has no surviving heirs, under the
No one has
claim to that land, period, possibly ever regardless of it being fulfilled in Joshua.
So before Joshua, they didn't have any claim to it, right?
So that doesn't really work, right?
But that hasn't stopped the Hasmonians and those with similar ideologies from trying to do
so in history.
the model we find and if you're a long time
the show that you'll be at least somewhat familiar with from other places we've talked about it,
that you find in places like the Testaments of the Twelve Patriarchs, is that this is the meaning
of Ephraim's destiny to become the fullness of the Gentiles, that essentially the people of
of the northern Kingdom of Israel were scattered among the nations like sea to scattered.
and they merged into those nations, but like Seed, the St. Paul says, for Seed to grow and has to first die.
So they as a people died, but now they as a people are going to be resurrected by people from those nations coming to worship,
Yeah, away they got a Israel and
Recon
constituting those 10 tribes.
And this, of course, as we pointed out, is what St. Paul is doing in Romans 11.
When he says that the heart of the Jews, the Judeans, Judah, has been hardened
until the fullness of the Gentiles has come in.
And so then once the fullness of the Gentiles
Ephraim has been added to the faithful remnant of Judah, then, as St. Paul says,
all Israel will be saved, all 12 tribes. And contained within that, that I don't
know if we've brought out before, remember St. Paul says that in the context of
Enromance 9 through 11, an extended argument about these answers to the
objection. Well wait, if Jesus of Nazareth is the Jewish
Messiah, why have most of the Jewish people not accepted him as the Messiah? And why
already within St. Paul's ministry were Gentiles, people from the nations,
non-Jewish Christians, quickly starting to outnumber Jewish Christians. If
Jesus had gathered earth is the Jewish Messiah. But think for a second, if St. Paul's
C's, non-Jews, Gentiles, who become Christians as being Ephraim.
The resurrected reconstituted Ephraim.
Ephraim was the most numerous tribe.
Ephraim was always bigger.
Ephraim always outnumbered Judah.
Bailah.
Yeah.
Right?
So it makes perfect sense, right, from St. Paul's perspective.
And so, you know, St. Paul makes it kind of explicit. He's writing a letter. But there are also places
narratively in the narrative of the New Testament. So we're talking about the Gospels and Acts, where
this is exactly how the Samaritans appear. The Samaritans in Samaria are the pivot point, the connection point
between
Judea, the Jewish people, and the faithful from the nations, and particularly in terms
of the Ministry of Christ himself.
One place where this is clear, where you've probably been waiting for us to go this whole
episode, is in John chapter 4, right, which is where Christ meets Saint-Photini, the Samaritan
woman at the well.
We're not gonna read that.
P-
part. You just heard that a few weeks ago in church, hopefully. The first part where he's
talking to St. Fotini, that's where most of the homilies go, including mine. I'm not talking
trash on anybody, most of mine due to you either preach about the conversation between Christ
and St. Fotini or the part that comes after what we're about to read, which is where it
talks about St. Fotini going and telling all the other people in her village about Christ,
coming to see him and saying first we believe because of your word now we have seen with our own eyes right so we talk about that element but there's this section in between that I think gets neglected a little bit that's the part we're about to read to see something that I think is important.
Okay, John chapter 4 starting with verse 27.
Just then his disciples came back. They marveled that he was talking with a woman, but no one said what do you seek or why are you talking with her?
So the woman left her water jar and went away into town and said to the
people come. See a man who told me all that I ever did can this be the
Christ? They went out of the town and were coming to him. Meanwhile, the
disciples were urging him saying, rabbi eat. But he said to them, I have food to
eat that you do not know about. So the disciples said to one another, is anyone
brought him something to eat? Jesus said to them, my food is to do the will of
him who sent me into accomplishes work. Do not say there are yet four months
then comes the harvest look I tell you lift up your eyes and see
that the fields are white for harvest, already the one who reaps is receiving wages and gathering fruit-free
eternal life so that so-er and reaper may rejoice together. For here the saying holds true,
one sows on another reaps, I sent you to reap that for which you did not labor, others have labored,
and you have entered into their labor.
So a couple of pieces here. And I was actually rereading this this year that inspired me to do this
episode. The review on the behind the scene.
thing. All right. So notice the harvest language, right? And he talks about, oh, someone
planted the seed, someone else a long time ago. He's in Samaria. And talking about the Samarins,
right? The seed was scattered a long time ago. But now it's time for the harvest.
And he says he's already doing the work.
That's how he characterizes his conversation with St. Potini.
He was beginning the harvest with her,
the harvest of Samaria of Ephraim, right?
And Christ is getting ready to send the apostles out where
to the nations, to harvest, right?
But remember, if you're...
harvesting, that means something was planted. It was planted a long time ago.
It was planted a long time ago. And that language of, I said, you to reap that for which you
did not labor, right? Others have labor, did you have entered into their labor? That's the language
that God uses over and over again in the Torah to describe Him.
bringing the people into the land. You're going to eat from vineyards you did not plant.
Right? You're going to harvest fields you did not sow. Right. So this is deliberately using
language of the reconstitution, the restart of Ephraim of the people in the land. Right? So
So, Saint John and a number of places in his gospel.
He doesn't write in Acts.
None of the other gospel writers write in Acts of the Apostles.
Right? Just St. Luke gives us that second chapter.
But St. John, all through his gospel,
telegraphs these things to us in other ways.
For example, it's in St. John's Gospel
that Christ breathes on the Apostles
and tells them to receive the Holy Spirit.
They might say, oh, wait, they didn't receive the Holy Spirit
Spirit of Pentecost. That was the whole point. There's supposed to be...
Jerusalem till they receive the Holy Spirit. Right? This is St. John telegraphing that. And so here,
St. John is telegraphing the apostles being sent out to the nations and the conversion of the Gentiles
and connecting it to seed, sown in Samaria. Pardon my eliteration.
But now let's go to actual act.
of the Apostles, right? St. Luke's Acts of the Apostles. Starting in chapter 1, let's begin at the beginning.
You also, if you went to liturgy for the ascension, have heard this recently.
Yeah. So starting with verse 6. So when they had come together, they asked him,
Lord, will you at this time restore the kingdom to Israel? He said to them,
It is not for you to know times or seasons that the father has fixed by his own authority,
but you will receive power.
when the Holy Spirit has come upon you, and you will be my witnesses in Jerusalem, and in Al-Judhiyah
and Samaria, and to the end of the earth. Right. So, a couple things to note here. Notice the question.
Will you at this time restore the kingdom to Israel?
Remember what we read in Ezekiel? How is the kingdom restored? Well, the kingdom is restored to
Israel.
When David right the Messiah
Who they now are identifying Christ as the Messiah very firmly? This is after the resurrection so now they're starting to get it
You're the Messiah are you now going to start the Kingdom of Israel are you now going to restore Israel?
Not Judah
Israel the whole thing all the tribes
right? And he says it's not for you to know the times that
and the seasons, right? But they're going to receive power. The Holy Spirit comes upon them and then
they're going to go out. They're going to go out where?
Judea and Samaria. At this point in history, Judea and Samaria are not separate Roman provinces.
Right.
So Judea and Samaria when Christ says it.
Those aren't separate places.
There's not a border between them on a map at the time he says that.
So he's talking about the people.
He's talking about the people.
You are going to reunite the Judeans of the Samarians.
They're going to do that by going to the ends of the world to all the nations
in order to reunite them so that he has the Messiah can rule over them.
And then we see this pattern play out.
Right there it's sort of set forth as the plan, but we see it play out in the actual text.
See that we go to Acts chapter 8 and say Philip.
All right. Starting with verse 4.
Now those who were scattered went about preaching the word.
Philip went down to the city of Samaria and proclaimed to them the Christ.
And the crowds with one accord paid attention
what was being said by Philip when they heard him and saw the signs that he did. For
unclean spirits crying out with a loud voice came out of many who had them and many who
were paralyzed or lame were healed. So there was much joy in that city. But there was
a man named Simon who had previously practiced magic in the city and amazed the people
of Samaria saying that he himself was somebody great. They all paid attention to him from
the least the greatest saying, this man is the power of God that is called great. And
They painted-
him because for a long time he had amazed them with his magic. But when they believed
Philip as he preached good news about the kingdom of God and the name of Jesus Christ,
they were baptized, both men and women. Even Simon himself believed, and after being
baptized he continued with Philip. And seeing signs and great miracles performed, he was
amazed. Now, when the apostles at Jerusalem heard that Samaria had received the Word of
God, they sensed to them Peter and John, who came down and prayed for them that they might
received.
the Holy Spirit. For he had not yet fallen on any of them, but they had only been baptized in the
name of the Lord Jesus. Then they laid their hands on them and they received the Holy Spirit.
Now, when Simon saw that the Spirit was given through the laying on of the Apostle's hands,
he offered the money, saying, give me this power also so that anyone on whom I lay my hands
may receive the Holy Spirit. But Peter said to him, may your silver perish with you because you
you thought you could obtain the gift of God with money.
You have neither part-
nor lot in this matter, for your heart is not right before God. Repent thereof for of this wickedness
of yours and pray to the Lord that if possible, the intent of your heart may be forgiven you.
For I see that you are in the gall of bitterness and in the bond of iniquity.
And Simon answered, pray for me to the Lord that nothing of what you have said make of upon me.
Now when they had testified and spoken the word of the Lord, they returned to Jerusalem,
preaching the gospel to many villages of the Samaritans.
Shhh.
So people are probably familiar with Simon Mayus, right?
And that part of the story, after whom Simon E.
The...
Yes.
He's in his name.
But,
may not remember that he was a Samaritan.
And that's where they ran into him.
But again, I don't want to focus on that more familiar part.
I want to focus on the less familiar part.
which is St. Philip comes and starts preaching to the Samarins, and notice he calls for St. Peter and
St. John to help him. These are the two surviving because Herod had killed St. James the
son of Zebidi shortly before this. Two surviving members of Christ's innermost circle of disciples
and apostles who come here and at the
We're told, go with St. Philip and are preaching the gospel in many villages.
They're going through all the villages of the Samarits and preaching the gospel.
And notice that St. Peter doing this, there's no this sermon
drawing that we get with Cornelius.
There's a like, oh, well, these are Samarits.
I mean, should I do this?
Should I go into their homes?
Should I preach to them?
Should we?
Yeah, no, there's no question.
There's no question.
Right.
Which means it says Peter and John, and I think we saw this reflected in St. John's Gospel,
right?
Who were there at Christ's words at the ascension, understood prophetically Samaria's
role, right?
Exactly how that dove tailed into the Gentiles, I think took a little longer to work out.
I think Saint Paul is the one...
who really presents that ultimately to the apostles at the Council of Jerusalem, right?
And everyone is then on board.
But Samaria they understand, right?
And so the pattern that we tend to have in our head of what happens with salvation in
the New Testament is that it goes, it begins with the Jews and then goes to the Gentiles,
really it's the Jews.
and then the Samaritans and then the Gentiles.
Yeah.
And Samaria is this pivot point, but also
with apologies to Monsieur Pagiot.
You want to talk about the symbolism of the Samaritans, right?
What is a pattern that we see emerging
in the history of the Samaritans tonight?
They are people who is emptied and then refilled.
who is disciplined and then restored.
Now it's repeatedly through their history.
Right?
And so within that symbolism, the idea that they are the vessel
through being emptied and refilled,
where ultimately the nations
will come to worship the God of Israel.
is the fulfillment of that pattern.
It's the ultimate and final form of that pattern as the testament of the 12 patriarchs
predicted that it's through Joseph who the Babylonians, the Assyrians, the Greeks, etc.
We'll find a portion of the inheritance of Israel, the inheritance of Abraham, the promises to Abraham.
So this is an incorporation that happens through Samaria.
And one of the questions I get, this will end up being my final comments too, I think,
one of the questions I get a lot when I'm talking about St. Paul and the Torah and this
element of the Gentiles being the resurrection, the restoration of Ephraim.
About that, I mean you and me.
I mean, Dutch guys like me, with the waiting guys like Father Andrew.
And whomever else, right?
Even from the question I get is, well, wait a minute, if we're part of Israel now,
doesn't that mean we're not Gentiles, right?
Does that mean then maybe we do have to follow the gravity of the Torah that were just
directed at Israel, right?
And...
The missing piece there is the one that I want to get at here in my final comments tonight,
which is notice that the goal, once Ephraim is restored from the fullness of the Gentiles,
right, is that all of the nations would bless the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel.
If all of the nations have become Israel,
That it would just say Israel was the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel.
Because the Ephraimites, right, while on one hand are the core of the promise are also
always not quite Israel.
not where the temple is.
They're not where the Messiah comes from.
They are and they aren't.
Why is that?
Well, this goes to something even deeper starting in the Torah in the Scriptures, which is
that the salvation of Israel is not an end in itself.
God.
does too in with and for Israel is done for all the nations.
And so there is always, there is the priesthood which is a minority within the people of Israel.
There is Judah which is a minority within the overall history of Israel.
There is the smaller portion and then there is the larger portion.
and the smaller portion benefits the larger portion.
This is a pattern.
And this carries forward to today.
The Church, Christ Church, the Holy Orthodox Church,
Church is a portion of the population of the earth.
But what God is doing in, to, with, and through His church is for the benefit and for the salvation of the whole world,
for the life of the world and for its salvation.
people who become part of Israel.
through Ephraim, do not lose their identities, but those identities are transformed and
reshaped to become followers of Christ.
And people who come into the church do not lose their identities.
But who you are as a person when you come into the church is transformed as a follower of Christ.
Not as an ended itself, but for the benefit and the salvation of the world.
You can't save the world by yourself.
It's not going to happen. You're not Christ.
You're definitely not going to do it on social media.
But you could be a part of saving your world, meaning your family, your friends, your co-workers,
the people in your life.
And it sounds hard, but it's not going to be as hard as you think if you really dedicated
yourself to it.
Because what makes it sound hard is that you're thinking you're going to have to change all those people or you're going to have to convince all those people.
You're going to have to talk things through and argue things through and work things out with all those people.
That's not the case. Really all you're going to have to do is work on yourself.
It's work out your own salvation.
Make that transformation of who you are, of your identity real.
dedicate yourself to following Christ. And when you do that, that transformation of
yourself and who you are will leak out into the world around you.
And we'll start to transform it to transform the people around you to. It will
happen. As soon as we get serious and focus upon it.
So, if you want to be a worker of the harvest, first harvest yourself.
First let yourself be ground down and baked into bread.
And then you'll have something to use to feed the people around you who are in need.
So, those are my final thoughts.
that occurs to me here at the end is um
You know, the one really prominent Samaritan in the scriptures that we didn't really talk
much about is of course the Good Samaritan.
And one of the things that occurs to me is that, you know, in the Gospels, Christ, he uses
this image of the Samaritan, the Good Samaritan, as the one who brings healing to the
who is beaten up by the side of the road.
And if you read, I mean, I've read a number of
pictures to commentaries on this passage.
And often what they basically will say is,
the good Samaritan is Christ.
The man who's beaten up is the soul and so forth.
And that, of course, is a very powerful and good
interpretation.
But one of the things that occurs to me is that,
The story that we've described as even about Samaria and Samaritans about how there's this broken kingdom.
There's idolatry and adultery.
There's tension, there's rivalry, there's mutual antipathy.
There's being smashed, there's conquest, there's all of these things, right?
That plays out, of course, we've looked at it play out in terms of this actual literal
people, but as Father just described, it works out in a really beautiful theological sense
in terms of the church, that the church is the fullness of the Gentiles is Ephraim.
is the return. But I think this also plays out again to borrow some some
Peugeotian language, this plays out fructively and also plays out on an
individual level like in your life, in my life. Even if you've been a Christian
your whole life, but if maybe you haven't, the story is playing out for you and
for your family, right?
That there's...
This not just imperfection, but maybe even adulteration.
Right? Like all of us are unfaithful.
And to some extent, faithful at the same time.
All of us are in that sense, heretical.
Right? All of us have this mixed baggage.
All of us have times when
and we're crushed when we're conquered.
All of us have times when we feel like we're just barely
hanging on.
All of us have times when we have revolted.
And yet we're all called to become this return,
to become the gathering in,
in say Paul's language, that all Israel may be saved.
And you're also to be the nations.
to be who we are that our experience through our lives is not erased and then replaced,
but we bring all of it with us and it becomes transfigured, perfected, that the darkness we've
experienced, the hurt that we've caused and repented of, becomes for us the basis of wisdom
and the basis of compassion.
And that as we look at Ephraim coming in in terms of the whole church, that the story plays
out on an individual level as well, and within a family as well, within friendships as well.
And the Christianity ultimately is this faith of hope that if...
If the people who are hated by the Jews can be redeemed,
can be Israel as well, and can even be an image that Christ uses
that the Church Father's interpret as being Christ,
this good Samaritan, if all that's possible,
then that means that wherever you've been,
whatever you've done, however you've...
failed, that can be you as well. You can participate in that. I can participate in that. And the key is
that faithfulness, that transformation that Father Stephen was just talking about.
Samaria becomes Israel again when Samaria is faithful to Yahweh.
And the good Samaritan is good because he is the one who does what is right.
So wherever you are at this point in your life, whatever your history has brought you to,
whatever your relationships are at this moment, whether they're in good shape or so-so or maybe pretty bad shape,
This can be our story. We can become...
Samaritans in this sense as well, we can be the re-gathering of Israel.
So you know it's late, but tomorrow is another day for repentance and tonight we have our evening prayers of repentance.
And that's what we have to do to worship Israel's God.
Because just as the Lord said to St. Fautini, Jacob's well there and what is now Nablus.
It's not about worshiping only in Jerusalem. It's not about worshiping only on Mount
Charism. Now it's everywhere. And worshiping God in Spirit and truth is possible for every
one. So every day you wake up and you sit yourself today, I begin again. Today I look at my
mixed messed up broken spotty whatever you want to call it.
it actually is history and my history still has this T-Lose that is aimed at Christ and
in Christ. And thank God for that. So that's our show for today, everybody. Thanks for listening.
If you didn't happen to get through us through to us live this time, we'd like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsNationFate.com. You can message us at our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits. And if you have basic
questions.
about Orthodox Christianity, or you need help to find a parish to do this stuff in 3D,
because that's where it's done.
Head over to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month.
It's 6 p.m. Eastern, 3 p.m. Pacific.
You got your puppy eyes.
You got your pitiful eyes.
I got one advice, a word of warning.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page.
You can join our discussion group and leave reviews and ratings in all the places.
most important, share this show with a...
friend. Finally be sure to go to ancientpaf.com
stroke support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasts stay on the
air. You thought that I could ease your mind. You thought that this I know if you
want help I should be last in line and I'll tell you why it's so. Thank you
good night and make our best of you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength.
and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.